<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A soveraign counter-poyson prepared by a faithfull hand for the speedy revivscence of Andrew Sall late sacrilegious apostat ... / Contriv'd by J. E.</title>
            <author>J. E.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171890</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299058</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179829</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03012)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179829)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2805:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A soveraign counter-poyson prepared by a faithfull hand for the speedy revivscence of Andrew Sall late sacrilegious apostat ... / Contriv'd by J. E.</title>
                  <author>J. E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Lonain [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, print show through with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinty College (Dublin, Ireland) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Soul --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179829:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179829:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Soveraign COUNTER-POYSON Prepared by a Faithfull Hand FOR The Speedy Reviviſcence OF ANDREW SALL Late Sacrilegious Apoſtat.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will ſerve to inform the ignorant, to reſolve the wavering, and to confirm the conſtant well-principled <hi>Roman-Catholick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contriv'd by <hi>J. E.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Inventi ſunt in Populo meo Impii inſidiantes quaſi aucupes, laqueos ponentes, &amp; pedicas ad capiendos viros.
<bibl>Jerem. 5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Noli eſſe ſtultus, &amp; ne impie agas multum ne moriar is tempore non tuo.
<bibl>Eccl. 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Lonain.</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:179829:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179829:2"/>
            <head>TO HER ROYAL HIGHNESS THE Dutcheſs of YORK.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Illuſtrious Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere is nothing in this world of more importance then to handle the affairs of Salvation with all earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; we well know we have an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſoul which ſhall ſurvive to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity either in the boſom of Glory, or in the flames of the damned; nothing is ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely confirm'd, as that none can be ſaved without true faith, and yet nothing by the malice of ſatan more controverted as the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of true faith. This ſmall Treatiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd in haſt for, and in vindication of, the verity of the ancient ſoul-ſaving faith of the Roman-Catholick Church, from the moſt miſterious and foul aſperſions and railings of the ignorant over-weening and over-byaſs'd Scioliſt Sectaries of this perverſe age, confidently flyes for to be ſheltred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wings of the moſt Renown'd Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of your Eminency, a moſt rare ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourer and vigorous practitioner of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Principles and tenents of the ſame ancient faith: what? an ineſtimable precious
<pb facs="tcp:179829:3"/>Jewel of fair, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and rich <hi>Modena,</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to all height of beauty and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orth (whoſe Royal blood of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ing nonour ſprings from the moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, moſt auguſt, and moſt heavenly ſtock and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oins of the Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> of that thrice noble and ancient houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> and of the moſt Catholick Kings of <hi>Spain,</hi>) now to contract ſtrong alliances with the uſefull and practical doctrin of the rare ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of pennance, humility, mortification, piety, charity and faſting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to fleſh and blood? what? a tender young, beauteous, eminently great Lady, ſeen often daily paying the Religious ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of heart, hand, &amp; knees to the Majeſty of the Almighty, by frequent retreats to a ſweet and undiſturbed Converſation with heaven, and this in the Royal Court, is the fair ſport of your beauteous minde, little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the tranſient vanities, guilded goades, and charming gaities, and allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a barren world, all which ends in folly and forgetfulneſs; O how mervelous is the power of ſolid vertue, when enchaced in pure beauty and glorious Extraction! Live then proſperouſly moſt pious Madam, and be ſtill a bright orient ſtar of the firſt magnitude, now auſpiciously fix'd in this Orb of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> ſhining, illuminating and warming (by your heroick and moſt
<pb facs="tcp:179829:3"/>examplar piety) frozen hearts in this cold for them Clime. Live then fortunatly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Madam who (by Gods ſweet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence) has been heightn'd to ſo ſublime merit, unparallel'd worth and admir'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments of all perfections as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Peerleſs Conſort of his Royal Highneſs <hi>James,</hi> that moſt gracious, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and moſt invincible Heroe, now the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated glory, the onely moving Soul, and moſt victorious Tutelar Angel of <hi>Great Britain:</hi> Live long and proſperouſly, Great Madam, until you enjoy in your boſom (through Gods bleſſings) a Princely Graff ariſing from ſo Noble, ſoveraign and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a ſtock, for the comfort and full joy and ſuccour of <hi>Great Britain.</hi> Moſt ſerene Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, this my Addreſs is far from a <hi>Panege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> in enlarging upon the eminent ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of your Endowments of minde and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; thoſe I leave for a fitter Subject of a higher Undertaking: Advance therefore Fair Madam your glorious progreſſions in vertues till you draw love and admiration even from your very Enemies (if any you can have.) I pray God to continue your Highneſs in all encreaſing proſperities, to bleſs your juſt deſigns, and to prolong your happy days, theſe ſhall be the daily vowes of me, who beſeeches your Highneſs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow one grace, which is, to permit me to
<pb facs="tcp:179829:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:179829:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:179829:5"/>bear all my life time the Title of your m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> humble and moſt Obedient Chaplain a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Beads-man,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. E.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:179829:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader</head>
            <p>THe reſtleſs and helliſh labours of ſome Pſeudo-prelates in compaſſing Sea and and for to make one proſelite, is very ſtrange; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ereas Apoſtates made their Apoſtles can be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tle purchaſe to Proteſtants, and the loſs of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an-Catholicks much leſs, they having been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce dead and cankereaten branches that could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r no fruit whilſt united to the ſtock and much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s now after their ſeparation: Their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ur is not to go far off and convert Pagans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m the worſhip of Devils and dead Idols, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve the living God, but rather to pervert il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>minated Chriſtians, corrupt and evacuate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>verity and ſoverainty of Chriſts faith by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vel devices, foul lyes and forgeries, is their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in ambition. The main reaſon therefore that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the Author upon the ſudden contrivement this ſmall Treatiſe, was ſeaſonably to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul and give a check to the diſingenuity, ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> malice, venome, and brawny-fac'd impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce of that renowned wight, vile Apoſtate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d profeſs'd Enemy to Chriſt, <hi>Andrew Sall:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> daſh back all his ſhameleſs affronts, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>undering, bawling ſtrains of profound and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nderful nonſence in his late open and avow'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ty practiſes at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and elſewhere (all better ſtuff then ould worn-out bold railings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d falſe ignorant ſtories of ſuperſtition, ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>try, Sacriledge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt the true mother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hurch for ſalvation) into his own teeth: The
<pb facs="tcp:179829:6"/>viper is ſo ſwell'd with venom and ree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that he muſt burſt or ſpit his poyſon ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, taking the liberty to amuſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing blinde deluded drove into popular rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, fluſh'd with the vain-glory he gain'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Proteſtants, ſtubbornly ſtruggles in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defence of that their daily dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying Sect, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then quitt the ſupport of his pride and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs: That God may preſerve mercif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſacred beams of his reveal'd faith in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hearts of Roman Catholicks, and ſecure th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the wiles ſnares and peſtilence of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtats that walked in darkneſs and deſtruction That the well-meaning may be cautious, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, zealous and careful in obſerving and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting inward motions, and that illuſions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not pervail over their underſtandings, inſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate into their deſignes, or unawares poyſon the beſt reſolutions. Finally that no Catholick his wits will intruſt his ſoul, and its eternal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to the blind conduct of ſuch ſhallow Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks, Impoſtors and runagate vagrant A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtats, is the ſcope of the publication hereof have not affected to ſet underſtandings on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rack by the Tyrany of ſtrong obſcure lines, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> meer itch of ſome vain wits of this Critick ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuch I wittingly wave: The Allmighty give proſperous bleſſing to it, with internal, exte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and eternal peace to Chriſts ſheepfold, the humble prayer of J. E.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179829:6"/>
               <head>Of the Happineſs of the Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Soul of man. 1. <hi>Document.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough we can never write, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any thing worthily of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence, yet we ought to make ſo good uſe of the objects of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior world, as to ſtudy our ſoveraign Creator in them, proceeding from the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects to the ſearch of the cauſe, which is the method of Philoſophy, whereas the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue proceeds commonly from the cauſe to the effect. The <hi>Pagan</hi> Philoſophers by the twilight of nature ſoar'd ſo high that they came to diſcover there was a <hi>primus Motor,</hi> an <hi>Ens entium,</hi> an <hi>optimus maximus,</hi> they came to know that he was ubiquitary and diffus'd through the Univerſe, to give vigor, life and motion to all parts though inviſibly. Now then, no finite created intellect can form a quidditative apprehenſion of God, no, not the Angels themſelves: there may
<pb facs="tcp:179829:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179829:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:179829:8"/>be negative conceptions of him, as to ſay, he is immortal, immenſe, independent, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and infinite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or, there may be relative Conceptions had of him, as when we call him Creator, Governour, King, Lord, Redeemer, ſanctifier, glorifier, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or there may be poſitive conceptions of him as the chiefeſt Good, a pure Act: or he may be deſcribed by an aggregation of Attributs, as merciful, wiſe, omnipotent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Among all theſe, one of the beſt wayes to diſcribe him is by abſtracts, as to call him goodneſs it ſelf, Juſtice it ſelf, power, wiſdom, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and mercy it ſelf; he being the Rule of all theſe; ſo as he is ſo incomprehenſible, as neither the Eloquence of <hi>Plato</hi> the divine, nor the ſubtility of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> whom S. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> ſtil'd the prodigy of nature, could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, or define by poſitive terms the meaſure of Gods being or Eſſence; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding S. <hi>Dioniſ. Areopagita, de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinis nomi.</hi> ſaid, <hi>Deus eſt convertens &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducens eos qui divinam in ſe corruperunt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem.</hi> God is ſo abſolutely powerful, as that he knows how to convert a moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ſinner: ſaying this, ſayes more then to call him Creator; though we may think, that the guift of Creation is greater then that of juſtification, becauſe <hi>Creati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eſt productio totius entis de non eſſe ad eſſe,</hi> doth preſupoſe the thing to be created only with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179829:8"/>an objective being, drawing it out of the abiſs of nothing; but Juſtification doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe the thing to be juſtified, <hi>a parte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> with a real phyſical being; yet the doctor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do agree in it that the Juſtification of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is greater then the Creation, for the repugnancy of contraries; for it's a greater work and more difficult to direct, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim one underſtanding miſled, and chaſe away, or diſpel the darkneſs wherein it is blindly involv'd, then to create the ſame of the new; and it's a more hard matter to ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or mollify a contumatious, obſtinate, depraved, and rebellious will, then to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the ſame of new. S. <hi>Thom.</hi> 12. queſt. 133. art. 9. ſaies <hi>bonum gratiae unius majus eſt quam bonum naturae totius univerſi,</hi> becauſe for to create a thing, the attribute of omnipotency doth ſuffice; but for to juſtify a ſinner, and cauſe him return to God, and loſt grace, requires all attributes, as omnipotency, mercy, wiſdom, prudence, goodneſs, of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So as that the rebellious and moſt obſtinate will of man renders the power of God doubtfull, or dubious, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ola voluntas humana facit dominium Dei dubium,</hi> all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary things obey God and his Saints, only the perverſe will of man ſpurns at God, and diſobeys him; was not the river turned into blood, obeying <hi>Moſes?</hi> did not the Rocks obey him and yield water?
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179829:9"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179829:9"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:179829:10"/>did not the Sun obey <hi>Joſuah,</hi> and ſtaied her courſe? did not the hungry Lions yield to <hi>Daniel?</hi> did not the whale preſerve <hi>Jonas?</hi> did not the mule kneel down and adore the B. Sacrament in S. <hi>Antony</hi> of <hi>Padua's</hi> hand? in effect, all things becoming pliable to God and his Saints: <hi>ſola voluntas humana</hi> is refractory, obſtinate, and rebellious againſt God. And it is a very ſtrange ponderation of the great Doctor <hi>Cirillus Jer ſolomitanus,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Quis poteſt eloqui Maris profundita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem? quod tamen intra ſuos limites ſe continet propter eum qui dixit huc uſque progrediaris &amp; non amplius, quandam lineam efficit in lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus ut oſtenderet intuentibus quod praefixos ſibi limites non tranſgreditur.</hi> Lord? what a furious and violent Element is the Sea, it would overflow all the Earth, had it not been, that God gave a command to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; yet the ſenceleſs Element ſtrictly obeys her God, and withall leaves twice a day a ſigne or mark of her due obedience to him; leaving both morning and evening a line of fome and froth on the ſhore, that all who paſs by, may take notice of her punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al obedience to her glorious maker. O what a main confuſion muſt this be to rational Creatures endued with will and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, bred to education, learning, piety, vertue, and Religion; and yet will not obey Gods commands; rather they will leave e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179829:10"/>day a ſignal mark of ſcandal, of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, againſt Conſcience, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion they profeſs, neglecting the wellfare of their Soul: <hi>ſola volunt as humana facit do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minium Dei dubium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reſtauration of man from ſin is a greater and more glorious work, then that of its firſt Creation, and its the utmoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of God in making the world. For God, having made all things for himſelf, and for the manifeſtation of his own Glory, as the wiſeſt end which he could propound to himſelf, was not ſatisfied with the firſt work of Creation, though exceeding good and perfect, but as ſoon as it was finiſh'd, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred ſin to enter upon the ſtage, bringing death and hell along with it: now all the wits of men and Angels could not unty this knot, ſin, til God came down from heaven and reſolv'd it into this moſt glorious work of Univerſal Redemption, pardoning ſin, as though it never was committed: and there is no other inſtance in the whole hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the World of any act of God, which doth ſo perfect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y exerciſe all his Attributes, and manifeſt all his Glory, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulfil the end of Creation, more then the Juſtification of the ſinner, in which God diſpoſeth all things ſtrongly and ſweetly, attracting man to him, and to the prefix'd end, calling, admoniſhing, illuminating,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179829:11"/>correcting, interiorly converſing with the heart, terrifying, inſtructing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet ſo as all is done without any Violence, becauſe he works Still ſweetly, and congruouſly to the liberty of free will, to wit, mollify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſweetly the heart of man, that divine Grace is not refuſed by the flinty heart: which is attracted not violently, but <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate &amp; voluptate,</hi> with an internal kind of delectation, and ſo tranſmits the ſoul ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, infallibly to the final end for which it has been created, by a ſweet efficaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and with an efficacious Sweetneſs: and this is effected by ſuch means and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that S. <hi>Paul</hi> in conſideration thereof, was conſtrained to ſay, O <hi>altitudo Sapientiae &amp; ſcientiae Dei!</hi> &amp;c. Alas! by what ſtrange way was S. <hi>Paul</hi> attracted by a voice and by light; S. <hi>Peter</hi> by one look of Chriſt: by another way was <hi>Magdalen,</hi> by teares; the <hi>Samaritan</hi> thirſting after the water of life was drawn: S. <hi>Mathew</hi> ſitting <hi>in telo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio</hi> drawn; the thief on the Croſs; <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Egipt</hi> from the Ordure of her libidinous luſt; <hi>Pelagia</hi> from her proſtitution, and ſordid queſt of whoredom; all theſe call'd away by ſeveral and unknown ways, to follow and purſue vertue, and the way to heaven; ſo as hereticks and haynous Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that ſits in the ſhade of death are illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated to apprehend their lamentable dark
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179829:11"/>ſtate, and look up to Eternity, and to the pure light of true life; making them, from the children of darkneſs to become the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of grace; and all this done by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly great wiſdom and Grace of God, without which, thoſe ſit in darkneſs of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and infidelity, in the imminent danger of eternal death, having their heart and underſtanding obſcure, ſo as that they are ignorant of God their Maker, ignorant of the way to heaven: ignorant of the final ſovereign happineſs for which they were created; and do not know themſelves, nor that they are children of wrath, and obnox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious to death, being ignorant of their own inſufficiency to good, ignorant of the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of grace and Regeneration, ignorant of Chriſt their Mediator, through whoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bloud they are reſtored from death to life: but by pure rays of divine faith they come to know all theſe things, and begin to look after earneſtly the way of Truth and of life, they implore grace, they invoke their Mediator, and ſeek after his ſoul-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Science and heavenly knowledge, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe words of S. <hi>Paul.</hi> 1 Corin. 4. <hi>ille qui de tenebris dixit lucem ſplendeſcere, ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe illuxit in cordibus noſtris,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:179829:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:179829:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:179829:13"/>
               <head>Of the true Eſſence of divine Faith. 2. Document.</head>
               <p>REaſon is moſt properly exerciſed in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings of nature, and Faith, in matters of Religion; great witts ſet up reaſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of faith, and the light of nature againſt divine light, which is at once to deprive man of his higheſt felicity and faculty; and God of his greateſt Grace: the ſame Word, without queſtion, which created the world creates a belief in a ſpiritual underſtanding, by relying on a divine reavealing Authority. Its moſt certain, that God is ſaid to <hi>Confound the wiſdome and learning of the wiſe by Faith,</hi> which declared, that without believing they cannot be ſaved, and yet without a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Grace they cannot believe; and as God is the chief good and perfect happineſs of the ſoul, and the object of our beatitude, which cannot be comprehended by natural light or knowledge, therefore a kinde of ſupernatural vertue is neceſſary, by which we may attain to his knowledge, which is ſaith, the higheſt knowledge we have in this world, by <hi>wch</hi> the ſoul injoys him, &amp; by him, the moſt excellent guifts and graces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is capable: according to S. <hi>Paul</hi> ad <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. <hi>gratia Dei eſtis ſalvati per fidem, &amp; hoc non ex vobis,</hi> Faith is that divine light by which we prepare our journy towards ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179829:13"/>and heaven; <hi>without faith it's impoſſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> pleaſe God.</hi> By faith Roman Catholicks do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alk upon the grounds of the Church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant, where there is infallibly an infuſion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abitual Grace, ſanctification in its ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and ſurely tranſcendent is their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation for their faithful conſervation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſacred Oracles of Truth in all ages, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his day, for their well ordered Zeale, for their moſt raviſhing devotions, deiform in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entions, their heroycal acts of faſting, praying, recollections, meditations, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roverſies, their aſpirations, humiliations, mortifications, abnegation of themſelves, and their dayly abdication of all tranſitory things; ſo as none in his ſences can believe, that ſuch a tree can be Corrupted in the root, which brings forth ſuch heavenly fruits. Some properties we may obſerve of the doctrine of Faith, to be true, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed of God, to be preached and delivered by the B. Apoſtles: The higheſt ground by which a man is perſwaded that his faith is true, is the Authority of God ſpeaking and revealing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the higheſt proof by which a man may be aſſured that his Faith is revealed, is the Authority of Chriſt and his B. Apoſtles, who delivered and preached the ſame as from God; and that from the beginning to this day it is practiſed without innovation or alteration, in all parts of the inhabitable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179829:14"/>world. The Apoſtles in the time of Chriſt converſing with them, had ſufficient Fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to prevail with their wills to command the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> underſtanding into the belief of his being God and man, conſequently an infallibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith; then it doth follow, that whatſoeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he taught was to be aſſented unto as infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly true, and that without being queſtione<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by our weak and limited reaſon: And ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this was very neceſſary for the true Church otherwiſe they could not have been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently aſſured, that what Chriſt their Maſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> taught them was true, and ſo it would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have been a ſin in them to have doubted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> This infallible aſſurance alſo, the Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that lived in the B. Apoſtles time, and afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt Aſcenſion enjoied; they had ſufficien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ground, without queſtion, to induce them to a belief that the B. Apoſtles were infallible Guides and Teachers, and that whatſoever they taught and commanded, was as infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly true, as if God had immediately ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſame things, and no more to be doubted, contradicted, or diſputed againſt, by vain and curious Reaſon (which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs were as ſtrong and as good as ours) then the immediate words, command, or dictates of Allmighty God; otherwiſe theſe who refuſed to hear and obey them, had beenin no fault; and it would have been an inſufferable boldneſs in S. <hi>Paul</hi> to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179829:14"/>ſuch an abſolute ſubmiſſion to what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> taught, as to oblige Chriſtians of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, not to have believed, even an Angel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om heaven, teaching contrary things to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he taught them. Hence it is, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>maining writings of the B. Apoſtles are by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll Chriſtians eſteemed as the word of God: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd this was mainly neceſſary, in the ages <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fter Chriſt, for the Church of God in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Apoſtles time, to have a living infallible way of direction, and this was the way to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aintain the <hi>unity of the ſpirit in the bond of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eace,</hi> &amp; ſo become one body; with one heart; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot as ſects divided, ſubdivided, &amp; ſcattered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>to as many parts, and ſorts as now are, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd have gone to cuffs, raiſing civil war for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he diciding of controverſies, as we have ſeen they did, ſince they divided themſelves from the holy Catholick Roman Church. Mark now thoſe words <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>without faith its impoſſible to pleaſe God:</hi> and of <hi>Math.</hi> 16.16. <hi>he that believeth ſhall not be damned;</hi> and <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5. <hi>there is but one faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, one Lord Jeſus:</hi> the faith which is to ſave us and by the which we are to pleaſe God cannot be had but in one Church, and that of Chriſt; it cannot therefore be found in Sects, in contrary opinions, it being of neceſſity but one, &amp; of contraries one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſt be true; Do but obſerve, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. <hi>bringing into Captivity every thought to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179829:15"/>obedience of Chriſt;</hi> that this faith or beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving was to be ſealed in the underſtanding that the underſtanding was to ſubmit, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> arrogantly to diſpute: And that this Act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>believe,</hi> was a command, or precept of Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mighty God, who will have his will obeye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by all his ſubjects, and the not obeying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is puniſhed with eternal damnat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Laſtly, conſider, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.23. <hi>let us ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> faſt the profeſſion of our faith, without waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for he is faithfull that hath promiſed</hi> That faith is truly divine, muſt be an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſent of our underſtanding, ſubmitting it ſelf obediently to believe the Revelation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>God;</hi> for otherwiſe faith, &amp; conſequently all Religion may be no more then fancy, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> opinion, and then no ways certain; and if ſo, then no obligation. Now it muſt follow, firſt, that there muſt be ſome means appointed by God by which we may know this one true faith, from all falſe Sects, and opinions, whereas to require one to believe upon pain of damnation, &amp; not to give him any means whereby he may know what to believe for ſalvation, in this Religion, or that ſect, were to require him to walk without leggs; theſe means muſt be infallible: for we cannot be brought to an infallible aſſent by fallible, and uncertain means, as God would not require us to aſſent to an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which may deceive us: then our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179829:15"/>muſt of neceſſity ſubmit to thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eans under pain of damnation. O terrible! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r if our underſtanding were at liberty to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bmit or not ſubmit to the means, by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ving Faith is conveyed unto us, it would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en be no ſin, not to believe, conſequently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od would not jnſtly damn us for not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eving; and withall, whoſoever ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe to be governed by thoſe heavenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eans, and the ſame authority that God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath appointed to govern us, he ſhall be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebel againſt God, and a vile Traitor. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, I ſay, that two men of two differing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iths or beliefs cannot be ſaved, for both of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem, knowing that they are bound to be guided and governed by thoſe means which God hath appointed, to convey ſaving faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o them, and one of them flatly refuſing to ſubmit, this perſon who refufeth muſt be guilty of diſobedience, and refractorineſs to Gods Command, and conſequently can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaved. And ſo to our preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ignorant people by reaſonable and earneſt diligence (as it is very tollerable to humane frailty, and very poſſible and eaſy for them) may come by Gods grace, to the true knowledge of theſe means, otherwiſe God would have appointed means, which would prove unprofitable to the end; and ſo, the far greater number of ſouls, for whom Chriſt died, would not be ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179829:16"/>for, by Gods ſweet providence, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that propheſy would prove alſo ineffectual Eſay. 35. <hi>Say to them that are of a fear f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> heart, be ſtrong: fear not, behold, your G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> will come, and ſave you, then the eyes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> blinde ſhall be opened, and the eares of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deaf unſtopped,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and one high way ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> there, and a way, and it ſhall be called the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way, that way-faring men, though fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall not err therein.</hi> It cannot be denyed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this wholſome doctrine is agreeable with all ſorts of people, Apoſtats, ſectaries, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diſſenters from the Mother Church for it muſt be granted that there muſt be a way and a Rule, there muſt be means appointed there muſt be a governing power to judge and decide all ariſing doubts, and teach a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the world the true way and path to heaven with certainty: but when we come to find<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it out, all perſons will agree, That they are obliged under pain of damnation to ſubmit to it, receive it, and embrace it, and wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> according to it, as to the Apoſtles, if they were actually living, or to Chriſt himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and when you underſtand this Rule and guide, then you cannot but believe all and every article of faith, which we the Roman Catholicks did all along, from the Apoſtles time, and this day, do unanimouſly believe, and practiſe; this is the main point which will allay all controverſies, conteſts, wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179829:16"/>ammoſityes and hatred between Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks, and all diſſenters: the God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f union and truth open the eyes, and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inate the underſtandings of apoſtats, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake right uſe of this my labour: Now I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t them know, that neither private ſpirit, or natural reaſon of any man, can poſſibly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this Rule, and Judge: for this muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it as a ſubject and Vaſſal to that Rule and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udge, and it's always fallible, and ſtrangdly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to miſtake &amp; miſleade; which is againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e nature of the true Rule and Judge to be: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r if God ſhould oblige us upon pain of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amnation to ſubmit unto, and to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erned and ruled by an Authority that might receive, and might teach for a truth what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not, we ſhould be bound to believe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> true, which is not ſo; and yet be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d, for not believing the truth: further, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our private ſpirit or reaſon were to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Rule and Judge, then it would follow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntrary to the ſcripture, that it is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſible to pleaſe God without faith, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aſon would ſufficiently teach us, how to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſe God, yet it would be a breach of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ule, to believe what we do not underſtand; would likewiſe follow, that every pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nded Religion would be the truth, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> contradictions would be true, and there would be not only one faith, but no faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all, but reaſon, above which faith is:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179829:17"/>for reaſon excludeth faith, and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſcarce that man living, but his reaſon diffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from anothers underſtanding; &amp; judgmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> differing as much as their faces: therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> none that follows his own Reaſon, could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> juſtice be condemned by God, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ilation, all men would be ſaved, unle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> peradventure you will ſay, that in a bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch main conſequence, as the ſalv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſouls, our primate reaſon perſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us to prefer the authority of ſuch, as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wiſer then our ſelves, before our own jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which is moſt true: But I then infe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that Roman Catholicks are the moſt rati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, moſt learned, moſt wiſe, moſt godly moſt unbiaſed people now in the world, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſequently have the beſt Religion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> acting moſt conformably to reaſon in the belief; for they rely ſtill on the authority <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> General Councils, conſiſting of the able and moſt learned men of all Nations, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is the greateſt authority to be found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Earth; eſpecially having the aſſiſtance of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> holy Ghoſt, <hi>viſum eſt ſpiritui ſancto, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> bis,</hi> as it appears they have, both by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> teſtimony of the Scripture, and the conſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> tradition of all ages: Upon theſe ground we may be ſure, that certainly God in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> good providence had appointed a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſure Guide, Rule, and Judge, to bring ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the infallible faith for ſalvation, the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179829:17"/>Reaſon and proud ſpirit; otherwiſe God is defective in neceſſaries, and that Religion were no more then fancy and opinion: and it is worth obſervation, how for the firſt two thouſand years before any Scriptures were written, the viſible Church of God was this Rule and Judge; was not, I pray, circumciſion and other Rites brought in by <hi>Abraham,</hi> and practiſed by the Church then, without any Scriptures to try them by? what would you have ſaid, if you had then lived? would you have diſobeyed the then Church, and reject thoſe ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe then there were no Scriptures to warrant them: The Church of the Jews was ſo to the Jews, after that the Scripture was written, and this by the expreſs dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Scripture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. <hi>Thou ſhalt come to the Prieſts, the Levites, and unto the Judge, and enquire, and they ſhall ſhew thee the ſentence of judgments,</hi> &amp;c. and then, <hi>he that ſhall do preſumptuouſly, and will not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto the prieſt or judge, even that man ſhall die;</hi> and even Chriſt whilſt the Jews, his Church, was yet in being, gave directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.2, 3. <hi>The Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees ſit in</hi> Moſes <hi>chair, all therefore whatſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and do:</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly God would not direct them and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them with death for not obeying an authority which might deceive and miſleade
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179829:18"/>them; would our Lord command the doing of whatſoever ſhould be done by an autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, when that authority was capable of miſtakings? the Church therefore, and not the ſcriptures was the Rule, and Judge to them, they were to hearken to the prieſt, and Judge, upon pain of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The happineſs of Chriſtian Religion. Document 3.</head>
               <p>REligion is a ſacred vertue of a Superior and divine nature, attended with an awfull reſpect to the worſhip of one Living God without any ſuperſtion in ceremonious obſervance, and withall it may be called the Law of the ſupreme King, commanding and directing that duty and worſhip which man owes unto him, and rewarding man with that true happineſs which he may enjoy in him: the <hi>Athenians</hi> inſcribed their Altar, <hi>To the unknown God,</hi> and their worſhip was as vain and ignorant, <hi>whom therefore</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>ye ignorantly worſhip, him I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto you,</hi> where he plainly ſheweth the difference between heatheniſh worſhip of God and true Religion: it's true, they had ſome glimmering apprehenſions of God, but they abuſed it with their Idolatry, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted it with their lives: S. <hi>Paul</hi> directly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179829:18"/>encountred the <hi>Athenian</hi> Idolatry, plainly preaching to the people the doctrine of the Deity, of creation, providence, ſin, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, Repentance, Reſurrection and the laſt Judgment: Thus Poets frame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion according to their fancy, vain philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers according to their imperfect Reaſon, ſtates-men ſhape it according to policy and Reaſon of ſtate, but the ſumme and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of true Religion is ſincerely to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, worſhip, love, fear, and reverence the living God, with heart, ſoul, and might; in the practiſe of vertues, which leads to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of glory. Holy and antient Religion is the <hi>Baſis</hi> of the permanent felicity of kingdoms; and Religion is ſaid a <hi>Religan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> it binds hearts, wills, nowriſheth pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſocieties, obſerves ſtrictly lawes: if it be changed, nought but confuſion, diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, darkneſs, diſcontent, diſunion, diſcord, and animoſities, can be expected to follow, all which <hi>Germany, England, Flanders, France, &amp; Ireland,</hi> can by wofull experience publiſh. In all ages it was neceſſary to make open profeſſion of Religion, in acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of humane and exterior worſhip to a Deity. S. <hi>Jerom</hi> doth advertiſe, That by Tradition of the Hebrews in the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the firſt begotten had right to the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of prieſthood, offering ſacrifice untill <hi>Aarons</hi> time: <hi>Adam</hi> by divine inſtinct in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179829:19"/>his Son <hi>Abel</hi> to offer ſacrifice to God, to fear and love God, for when <hi>Cain</hi> ſaid, there is no Judgment to come, no Judge, no other world but this, no reward for the Jult, no puniſhments for ſinners, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this world is governed by Gods mercy; to whom <hi>Abel</hi> the defender of Truth repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>frator ne ſic aſſer as erroniè eſt enim Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium eſt Judex, eſt aliud ſaeculum, eſt ibi mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces pro juſtis, &amp; poena pro Impiis.</hi> Gen. 4. But in the Moyſaical law, the levits were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen prieſts, <hi>Num.</hi> 3. who had power to offer ſacrifice to God, then <hi>Abraham, Jſaac, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Joſeph,</hi> with 12 Patriarks; after theſe came <hi>Moſes, Aaron, Joſue,</hi> together with the 72 Elders that governed the People, with many Prieſts and Prophets, all exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Religion, offering ſacrifice: four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after came <hi>David, Samuel</hi> and <hi>Nathan,</hi> with many holy Prophets; after God ſent <hi>Jeremy, Ezekiel, Daniel, Zachary, Aggeus, Malachy, Nehemias,</hi> &amp;c. for to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Religion, divine worſhip, Sacrifice, faith and Sacrament; now I ask, what's the reaſon that now under the holy law of the Goſpel, Proteſtants have no ſacrifice, the principal point of Religion? it is, becauſe they have no Prieſts with true character, function, holy Orders, Miſſion, power, and authority, from above, but from the weak arm of fleſh; therefore having no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:179829:19"/>true Prieſts, no Religion, no Sacrifice, no Sacrament, no faith, but opinion and fancy; But the Roman-Catholick Church, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Miſtriſſe of true faith, hath law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prieſts, Religion, Altars, Sacrifice, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, ſucceſſive function of Prieſthood, eſtabliſhed by Chriſt, for the perpetuity of his Church, and comfort of his flock. O mercy and divine providence never to be duely pondered! now the infernal Dragon, a declared enemy to God, becauſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come near him to hurt or offend him, he hurts man the Image of God, even as he that is an enemy to a father of a family, when he cannot annoy his perſon, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to annoy his poſſeſſions, his fields, his children; ſo the devil, caſt from Heaven by God, hath ſtill enmity againſt him, but not being able to annoy God, he endeavours to deſtroy man Gods image, to pervert him, to delude him and divert him from true Religion, alledging, that Chriſt's Church is not the true Church, that it's er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, ſuperſtitious, full of ceremonys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You may reade in <hi>apoc.</hi> 16. <hi>vidi prodire de ore draconis:</hi> I have ſeen coming out of the mouth of the dragon, the beaſt, the pſeudo-prophet, three foul ſpirits like froggs; this dragon, this beaſt, this pſeudo-prophet is <hi>Luther:</hi> the three froggs are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by many Interpreters, the three
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179829:20"/>perverſe ſordid Sects, which did flow from curſed <hi>Luther:</hi> the firſt, that of <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> whoſe firſt Author was one <hi>Roſmanus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>Lutheran:</hi> the ſecond that of <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries,</hi> the Author whereof was <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſtadius,</hi> from whom proceeded <hi>Zuinglius</hi> and <hi>Calvin:</hi> the third is that of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> whoſe Author was <hi>Melanchton,</hi> or rather <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. for before his diſmal Revolt from the Roman Religion, there was for 1500. years and above, no other Religion in <hi>England</hi> but the Roman Catholick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, flowriſhing moſt gloriouſly, in piety, learning, ſanctity, proſperity and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, having had 22. Kings in the opinion of Saints, and no memory, dream or word of Proteſtant in <hi>England</hi> before his Reigne. And not unfitly hereſy is compared to frogs for ſordidneſs, loquacity, and for importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, for ſtill you may hear the frogs in quagmires, with their harſh unpleaſant and troubleſome clamors night and day, to which the clamors of hereticks is very like: and <hi>Pierus.</hi> l. 19. de <hi>Rana.</hi> ſays, that the frog hath bloudy red eyes, and that it hath a double liver, properties of hereticks, their eyes are bloody, looking with eyes of fleſh and blood upon the miſteries of Religion, the power of the Pope, looking with eys of blood upon the power of abſolving given to the Prieſts, ſeaven Sacraments, the Real
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179829:20"/>Preſence; all they look on with eyes, not of faith but bloud; Two livers alſo, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, no faſting, no auſterity of life; no mortification, no pennance but ſtill eat, drink, take pleaſure, fare well, ſtill increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing blood in their two livers, the ſeat of blood, for to purſue luſt, and concupiſence, and an unbridled appetite of their fleſh and blood, and which muſt breed and nouriſh pride, the ſource and nurſery of hereſie; according to S. <hi>Auſtin: diverſae diverſis locis ſunt haereſes, ſed una mater ſuperbia genuit:</hi> it is ſaid, that the Camel is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to drink before he troubles the water, ſo hereſy never enter'd into any kingdom, but by troubling the Republicks with diſſentions, civil broils, <hi>quia domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ſpernunt, &amp; Majeſtatem blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, ut ſerpentes humiliter irrepunt, blande capiunt, molliter ligant, latenter occidunt:</hi> with their Serpentine <hi>cur praecepit vobis deus</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve;</hi> ſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks are like ſerpents <hi>cur tot praecepta? cur tot jejunia? cur diebus veneris carnes vetitae? cur tot in Eccleſia ceremoniae? cur &amp; quomodo corpus Chriſti in exigua panis ſpecie?</hi> &amp;c. Are not theſe ſerpentine interogations? all their ſtir is but from ſence, from fleſh and blood, for honor, for plauſible exteriority: Did not <hi>Melancthon</hi> the firſt follower of <hi>Luther,</hi> tell his Mother at the point of death
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179829:21"/>that the proteſtant was <hi>plauſibilior,</hi> but the Catholick Religion <hi>ſecurior,</hi> whereupon his Mother ſent for a Roman Catholick prieſt, and died in the boſome of the true Church for ſalvation; <hi>haec plauſibiliòr illa ſecurior;</hi> Did not a Gentleman ſay, <hi>Si bonum eſt cum Luthero vivere, haud bonum eſt cum Luthero mori;</hi> and did not <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf ſay, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Martine, jam agis voluptuoſe, ſed quid erit poſt haec?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>A Soveraign connter-poyſon. Document 4.</head>
               <p>S. <hi>Cyyrian</hi> the great Doctor, writing to ſome of the Ethnicks, touching the lives and ſtudies of Chriſtians, ſpeaks thus, <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophi ſumus factis non verbis, nec magna loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, ſed vivimus,</hi> that is, we are philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers in our actions, not in our words, nor do ſpeak great things but practiſe them. It ſeemes, this holy man thought it much fitter for a Chriſtian to exerciſe himſelf in Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions, then in diving with curioſity into the Nature of things. <hi>Andrew Sall,</hi> When I conſider your preſent miſerable ſtate and deplorable condition, I cannot ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from tears; you have been heretofore known and counted a philoſopher both by words, and deeds; you ſpoke great things,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:179829:21"/>and did likwiſe practiſe them: But alas! alas! lately there is ſeen and perceived in you a ſtrange and ſudden alteration and change: I ask, <hi>quomodo obſcuratum eſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum? mutatus eſt color optimus?</hi> thren. 4. you ſeem awhile ago pure precious gold, how come you metamorphoſed and chang'd, ſo as no ſhaddow could vaniſh halfe ſo ſoon? now, not gold, <hi>ſed fuligo,</hi> droſs and rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſ <hi>quomodo mutatus eſt color optimus?</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore a religious prieſt, an Embaſſadour for atonement of grace and mercy, a preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, all thoſe ſuperexcellent prerogatives, graces, and beauties defaced? what? a living member of the glorious Congregation of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus become a dead child of error, hereſies &amp; darkneſs, and ſuddenly become the ſcorn of boys and Lackies ſure this cannot be, <hi>muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio dextrae Eccelſi:</hi> ah poor <hi>Andrew!</hi> That exquiſite torment uſed in antient times by Tyrants to their Captives hath ſome imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect weak reſemblance of your poor ſouls preſent condition; they uſed to faſten li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving men to dead bodies, joyning their hands, their feet, their mouths, their eyes, and all their other parts with thoſe of dead putrid carcaſes; <hi>Corpora corporibus jungebant mortua vivis;</hi> Let us conſider, what were the thoughts of thoſe miſerable wretches, who though living, were by this union hindred from exerciſing any the actions of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179829:22"/>life; and notwithſtanding their natural aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from ſtench, rottenneſs and corruption, were yet forced to converſe only with them, exchanging all the happineſs of life to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thoſe diſmal objects which preſented them with nought but ghaſtlineſs &amp; terror, all this <hi>Andrew</hi> is an imperfect repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your ſtate; you cannot but perceive your living body to be faſtned to a loathſom dead ſoul, and ſo by that unhappy union, you are hindred from exerciſing any actions of grace or vertue, yet are forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe only with the Father of darkneſs, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding your naturall averſion from him, and this for your ſacrilegious Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, and revolt from the mother Church, in which you had an unerring Guide, Rule, and Judge, leading you to true faith, the high path to laudable actions of grace, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification and eternal felicity: oh <hi>mutatus eſt color optimus;</hi> and this unhappineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell you, through the perverſe and wicked choiſe of your blind will: for what the ſoul is to your body, ſuch in a manner, I may ſay, is Gods divine Grace to your ſoul: all the members of your body, by the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoul are alive, do move and ſtir, and exerciſe their ſeveral functions, which when the ſoul is ſeparated from your body, all thoſe members are as dead as a ſtone, no member can ſtir or move, nor exerciſe its
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179829:22"/>function: even ſo when your ſoul is berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of Gods grace (as it is at preſent by black Apoſtaſie) then your ſoul is dead to all goodneſs, all the faculties and powers thereof cannot exerciſe their function in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to eternity, vertue, or ſanctity; you are quite blotted out of the book of life, and ſociety of Saints; you have no more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with the bleſſed and celeſtiall Congregation of the Church-militant; you have forfeited your claim and right to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; you cannot enjoy, as formerly, thoſe internal, ineffable joys, bleſſings, and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, which the true, conſtant ſervants of God, your fellow-travellers, and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labourers in the vineyard of Chriſt have, and your brethren hourly do taſte and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy; <hi>Corpora corporibus jungebant mortua vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis.</hi> Oh wretched <hi>Andrew!</hi> it had been more advantageous and of more pleaſure to you, to have your living body faſtned to a rotten putrid carcaſe, then to have your ſoul faſtned to darkneſs, and lothſomneſſe of curſed hereſie and apoſtaſie: Now, do but conſider the infinite advantage, preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and dignity of your former happy ſtate, and compare it to your preſent deplorable, curſed and moſt black ſtate: before you were <hi>vir Apoſtolicus,</hi> now <hi>apoſtata vilis dictus;</hi> before a moſt reſplendent ſtar in the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the true Church, now an obſcure,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:179829:23"/>dusky, and abominable <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> leading your ſelf and, thers to precipices of eterna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perdition; before a Religious prieſt, now an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> accurſed <hi>Judas;</hi> before conferring life of grace on others, now you are left deſtitute, and naked; ſtripped of all light life, grace, bleſſing and goodneſs; before call'd by the hand of God to a moſt high and ſoveraigne dignity and honour, now blindly fallen from that, moſt lamentably, to the devils jaws; before an obedient child, now <hi>factus liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> voti-fragus;</hi> before a chaſte and Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Miſſioner, now <hi>ſacrilegus ſcortator;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reputed an honeſt man, <hi>queſtuoſus mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator,</hi> now <hi>fugitivus Apoſtata, &amp; ſeditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſectarius factus;</hi> before rasi'd from a <hi>Sall</hi> to be a <hi>Paul,</hi> a preacher of the word and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, now turn'd to be a <hi>Sall</hi> perſecuting, &amp; warring in a moſt furious manner againſt the heavenly fortreſs of true faith, the pillar and foundation of truth, and ſo become a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, Iying and vile proteſtant; wallowing like a naſty ſordid, and ſtinking ſow in the mire of liberty, libidinous luſt, pride, and concupiſcence: retire retire, poor <hi>Andrew!</hi> to your interiour man, have a care of your drooping ſoul, minde eternity;</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>fieres ſi ſcires tuum tua tempora menſem,</l>
                  <l>rides cum non ſit forſitan una dies.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Micheas</hi> underſtanding that he was rob'd of his domeſtick Idols, ran after the Robbers,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179829:23"/>crying moſt lamentably, and being queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, what was the matter with him? and why did he cry, mourn, and lament? he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, my gods which I made for my ſelf are ſtolen away, my prieſthood, which were all my riches and comfort, <hi>Jud.</hi> 18. all what ever was dear unto me taken away from me, therefore why ſhould I not mourn? I ask, if this wretch kept ſuch a deplorable ſtir for having loſt but Idols, he vainly i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined, that loſing them he loſt all that had been precious unto him; oh <hi>Andrew!</hi> why will you not grieve, cry, mourn, and with bitter tears lament, the loſſe of the true, living, and dreadfull God, for the loſſe of divine grace; of your ſacred function, of your fame and eſtimation, ſecurity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and the peace of your heart, the pledge of eternal glory? O madneſs! O blindneſs! oh woful cataſtrophe of apoſtaſy! Oh poor <hi>Andrew!</hi> you fell from the mother-Church, grounded not on ſands or quag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires, as proteſtaniſm, into which you miſerably declin'd: you imagine to impugn and beat down the glory, luſtre and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of the ſame: alas! alas! all your ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome you may ſpit, and bark like a maſtiff, and fill the ears of your deluded audients with thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould railing, and lying empty aſſertions, calling the Roman Church ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, erroneous, the horrid beaſt, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179829:24"/>the whore of <hi>Babilon,</hi> and ſuch like, <hi>ſapius &amp; indies repetita</hi> in your tub-pulpits: but all ſignifies nothing but to heap judgments and confuſion on your head: oh <hi>Andrew!</hi> all ſhall recoile upon you,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Niteris incaſſum Petri ſubmergere Navem,</l>
                  <l>fluctuat, aſt nunquam mergitur illa Ratis:</l>
               </lg>
               <p>you deſerted a Church, in which one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is Faith, Religion, prieſts, Sacrifice, Altars, Sacraments, and Reall Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not onely of original ſinne, but alſo of actual mortal ſins, all which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and exploded, and quite aboliſhed by your proteſtant Sect, as it's prov'd in the <hi>Reaſonable Reply to the ſeaſonable diſcourſe.</hi> you deſerted a Church, out of which there are no ſure inducements or means for ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for there can be but one true Church left by Chriſt, out of which no aſſurance of his doctrine, nor of the divine ordinance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by him for ſalvation: mark pray, what S. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. ſays, <hi>erit unum ovile &amp; unus paſtor, there will be one fold and one paſtor:</hi> one fold ordained by Chriſt, that is, one viſible Congregation of men in a common union of one faith and government under one viſible paſtor, Univerſal Vice-gerent of Chriſt, and undoubted Succeſſor of S.<hi>Peter,</hi> with true Orthodox preachers, with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſacred ordinances, obliging all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful under pain of eternal damnation, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:179829:24"/>follow, and practiſe the ſame, with an abſolute promiſe to maintain it to the end of the world by divine protection: but alas! poor <hi>Andrew!</hi> you well know in your Conſcience that no other Sect or viſible Congregation could yet have or enjoy theſe divine, and ſupernatural qualifications and heavenly perfections, but only the Roman Catholick Church, therefore the ſame and no other is the one fold, and one congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, enjoying, without intermiſſion, one Viſible Univerſal paſtor, in communion with one faith neceſſary for ſalvation. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this Church onely hath a viſible head, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nder an inviſible head, Chriſt, <hi>tu es Petrus &amp; ſuper hanc Petram,</hi> &amp;c. the delivering the Keys of heaven to <hi>Peter</hi> is nought elſe but a full and ſoveraign power for to govern the Church, to him ſaid Chriſt, <hi>paſce oves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eas, &amp; tu aliquando confirma fratres tuos;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o one of the other Apoſtles were theſe words intimated, but to <hi>Peter</hi> only: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks will reply, that all the Apoſtles recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved plenary power for binding and abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; I anſwer, that the reſt of the Apoſtles received immediatly that power from Chriſt, yet the power of <hi>Peter</hi> has been more abſolute and excellent, becauſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that power as ordinary, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore did flow and doth paſſe to his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; the reſt of the Apoſtles only received
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179829:25"/>a <hi>delegate power,</hi> which do not paſſe to thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſucceſſors, but is in them expired, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> S. <hi>Peters</hi> power was abſolute and the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, to which the power of the reſt had al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ways as annexed to it a kinde of ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and ſubjection to <hi>Peter;</hi> to whom only Chriſt ſaid, <hi>tibi dabo claves; paſce ove<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meas, &amp; agnos meos, confirma fratres tuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> againſt which the gates of hell ſhall neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prevail; that is, neither Turks, Pagans Jews, Hereticks, nor wicked livers, ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> never beat it down: hence he is called <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>put omnium Eccleſiarum, poteſtate &amp; autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritate <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis Patriarcha, Mater omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ſummus Pontifex, Apoſtolicae ſedis An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſtes, Eccleſiae Pater, Rector &amp; Caput;</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Juſtinianus</hi> the Emperour ſaid of him, <hi>ſum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mi Pontificatus apicem apud Romam eſſe nem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt qui dubitet, ad Romanam fidem perfidia no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> habet acceſſum,</hi> becauſe Chriſt ſaid, <hi>rogav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pro ſe Petre ut non deficiat fides tua:</hi> and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moved S. <hi>Jerom</hi> to ſay, that true Religion cannot be conſerved without the Empire o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a head, or great authority of an univerſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Paſtor and Vice-gerent of Chriſt; <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalus a ſummi ſacerdotis dignitate depende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> without which there will be made daily in finite ſchiſms, diviſions and ſubdiviſions i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kingdoms, as we may ſee now in poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>England:</hi> ſo as the true Church hath two heads, one inviſible <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt, <hi>fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:179829:25"/>aliud nemo poteſt ponere praeter id quod poſttum eſt, quod eſt Chriſtus,</hi> who is <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum fundamentorum:</hi> but <hi>Peter</hi> is the ſecond, cleaving to Chriſt, and placed on Chriſt: we believe in the firſt principal head or fundamental ſtone, Chriſt; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>Peter,</hi> wee onely obey: Chriſt is the primary foundation, <hi>baſis,</hi> and prop, of our faith, becauſe we believe all thoſe things to be true which he (as the firſt infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible verity) did reveal to be believed, we believe God to be one, and three, the word made fleſh, and ſo forth; not that <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> or <hi>John,</hi> or any <hi>Pape</hi> ſaid ſo, or taught the ſame, but that the firſt verity, God reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, propounded, and ſaid the ſame, ſo as our faith is founded on Chriſt; yet becauſe thoſe matters revealed by Chriſt are not ſo manifeſt what they are; he therefore gave us a ſecondary fundamental ſtone, <hi>Peter,</hi> and his ſucceſſors, who tells us, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds, what Chriſt revealed, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes ſuch, from what was not revealed or delivered by him, and ſo our faith is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on both ſtones, but in a different manner; the one is but vice king or Vicar; but Chriſt the prime and principal ſtone, communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Peter</hi> his Epithete, though it has been <hi>analogice tantum:</hi> It is very remarkable what happened in the time of <hi>Stephanus</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded <hi>pape</hi> 7. according to <hi>Baron.</hi> anno.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179829:26"/>897. how that <hi>Baſilica Lateran<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> the prime Pontifical ſeat, <hi>impulſore Angelo malo,</hi> did all fall down to the ground, even from the high Altar to the very gate; the ſanctuary only, in which was the Chair of the Pape being remain'd whole and entire; which ſtrange accident doth manifeſt, that the true ſeat of glorious S. <hi>Peter</hi> can never come to ruine, notwithſtanding that ſanctity and grace in heads and members may ſometimes fail: Becauſe Chriſt Jeſus that Eagle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the ſame, though he ſits in heaven, in his glory, yet he ſtill hath his ſacred eyes fixed on the neſt of his Church, to preſerve it till doomſday; even as when the Eagle hath his little ones in the neſt, fearing the poyſon of ſerpents, great enemies to his neſt and his young birds, he flies up and down among the Rocks for to finde out the precious ſtone called <hi>Aetites,</hi> or <hi>Eagleſtone,</hi> which the Eagle places in his neſt, which hat rare vertue againſt all venome: See <hi>Pierius valer.</hi> even ſo that glorious Eagle, Chriſt, left in his neſt, the Roman-Catholick Church, his heavenly ſpouſe, many preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Eagle-ſtones, <hi>viz.</hi> many places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture revealed by him, for to preſerve the ſame alwaies from the ſtinking breath and poyſon of accruing hereticks. Did not Chriſt place one Eagle-ſtone in the neſt of his Church when he ſaid, <hi>rogavi,</hi> Peter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:179829:26"/>
                  <hi>thy faith ſhall never fail:</hi> and S. <hi>Cyprian lib.</hi> 3. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 3. ſaid, that to the Roman faith perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs could have no acceſs: Another ſtone, <hi>Peter, feed my ſheep, feed my lambs;</hi> which preſerves <hi>Peter</hi> and his Succeſſors till the end of the world to be Univerſal Paſtors, Heads, and viſible Vicars of Chriſt in his viſible Congregation, from all malice, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and venome of barking hereticks. Are not the ſeven Sacraments proved and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellouſly preſerved from all venom by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Eagle-ſtones in Scripture: <hi>Confirmation</hi> has that ſtone <hi>Act.</hi> 8.15, 17. <hi>Pennance</hi> and <hi>Sacramental Confeſſion</hi> proved, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.18. and <hi>John</hi> 20.23. Saint <hi>James chapt.</hi> 5. from the dangerous venom of hereticks: withall obſerve <hi>Andrew,</hi> the terms of the Commiſſion granted to Roman-Catholick Prieſts to abſolve ſins are ſo large and general, that without great temerity, that power cannot be reſtrain'd, only unto publick and notorious offences; and when the Prieſt pronounces the <hi>Abſolution</hi> in the Name, and by the power of Jeſus, ſince he doth but follow the expreſs terms of their heavenly Commiſſion, the ſentence then is repeated as given by Chriſt himſelf, in whoſe place they are appointed as viſible Judges to the viſible members of Chriſt's viſible flock; ſo as it is the inviſible high-prieſt, <hi>viz,</hi> Chriſt, who interiorly abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179829:27"/>the penitent whilſt the prieſt exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the exterior Miniſtry. <hi>Extreme unction</hi> is confirmed and preſerved from the infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hereſie by that ſtone placed by Chriſt in his neſt, <hi>Jac.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Marriage</hi> likewiſe by that precious Eagle-ſtone, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.5. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.32. <hi>Holy Orders</hi> eſtabliſhed, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and preſerved from all poyſon, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. The <hi>Real Preſence</hi> of Chriſts Body in the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chariſt ſolemnly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from the venom and infection of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical, figurative underſtanding by thoſe Eagle-ſtones, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. <hi>Luke</hi> 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. 26. O brave militant Church, O tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of the pure neſt of Jeſus, where ſouls are ſaved, and conveied to the glory of the Triumphant Church, againſt this fortreſs of truth, againſt this Neſt and Spouſe of Chriſt; all what <hi>Andrew Sall,</hi> or freſher wits of the whole heap of Proteſtaniſm (begun diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly by the ſhameful revolt of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. and moulded and made up by the arm of fleſh) ſhall never prevail againſt it; and all that they ſay will be no more then ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeveral handfuls of execrable aſhes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the urns of condemn'd hereticks, whoſe malicious cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivements are quite forgotten: that Roman Catholicks are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, erroneous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is the onely chief rope whereupon the Apoſtate <hi>Sall</hi> dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the antick, and triumphs: which can
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179829:27"/>never be proved: empty, aerial &amp; ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe bare words can beguile none but weak licentious and fickle reeds, they will never prevail with any well-principled Chriſtian;</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>And though all tempeſts of the world aſſail</l>
                  <l>Chriſts faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>gainſt it hell cannot prevail.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andrew,</hi> eat your bread, hold your tongue, all you can ſay againſt Chriſt's ſacred neſt will ſignifie nothing, but as meer ſcare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crows; it can avail you nought elſe but heap judgements on your crazy head and palſey hand: come along ſweet <hi>Andrew,</hi> 'Tis worth your ſerious conſideration to ponder the glory and ſplendour of Roman-Catholick Religion; <hi>Saul</hi> from a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor by the hand and call of Chriſt became a Preacher, an Apoſtle; what greater confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Chriſtian Religion, then to ſee Chriſt appearing to preſerve his neſt and his ſpouſe from imminent danger, menaced by a cruel wolf <hi>Saul;</hi> the head preſerves the members, the glorious Eagle preſerves his little ones from the jaws of hell; the Scribes and Phariſees <hi>Math.</hi> 16. ſought for ſignes from heaven, lo now a moſt rare and ſtupendious one, Chriſt in the air forcing <hi>Saul</hi> to become <hi>Paul,</hi> and a main witneſſe of the truth of our Religion; here may be conſidered the ſtrength and certainty of our faith; an enemy of the Goſpel, Doctor of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179829:28"/>the Jews, to become in an inſtant, metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos'd and quite chang'd from a wolf into a meek lamb and preacher of Chriſt's law: how come <hi>Saul</hi> like another <hi>Balaam to bleſs the people of God,</hi> who was ſent <hi>to curſe them?</hi> but that he was conſtrained by God ſo to do, and has been taught in our faith by Chriſt himſelf moſt wonderfully. O <hi>Andrew Sall!</hi> this is no great comfort for you, who from a <hi>Sall</hi> was raiſed to be a preſt, a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, like another <hi>Paul;</hi> now to become a <hi>Saul,</hi> a wolf, an enemy, a perſecutor of Chriſt and his members, yea, even a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer: Return back, call for mercy, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, come and receive grace: <hi>Saul</hi> an enemy received grace, was made a choſen veſſel: O mercy never to be duely ponder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed! diſtruſt not wretched <hi>Andrew!</hi> diffide not of Gods goodneſs and mercy, nor of the efficacy of his divine grace: <hi>Sall, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quutus es errantem ſequere poenitentem Saulum?</hi> liſten to Gods calling, voice and illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtifle not the divine inſpirations of God, <hi>vocantis, illuminantis, arguentis, caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantis;</hi> ſay chearfully with S. <hi>Paul, Domine quid me vis facere!</hi> do not expect to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by God; <hi>ingredire Civitatem;</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your Court of <hi>Camas,</hi> come <hi>audi Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam, Concionatorem co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſolatorem, amicum, &amp; confeſſarium tuum fidelem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:179829:28"/>
               <head>A Soveraign Caution to Roman Catholicks, not to be troubled, or take ſcandal by <hi>Andrew Sall</hi> Apoſtate falling from his Religion. Documents 5.</head>
               <p>WHat Lay-man will not run and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly embrace a plauſible and eaſy way to heaven? ſure we cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant how ſtones fall naturally down to their centre, yet are with difficulty raiſed up; it's more facil to deſtroy and beat down a houſe then to build the ſame: Did not Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> Lord Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> and a glorious Martyr, make anſwer in this manner, to one who bragg'd much of the propagation of <hi>Luthers</hi> ſect, ſaying, <hi>ad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitam vitae libidinem &amp; licentiam, populum ruere, majus non est miraculum quam ſaxa deorſum cadere;</hi> take notice alſo how <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> anſwered a certain common ſtrumpet, who inſulted and ſaid, <hi>tu neminem ex ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus meis unquam valebis a me ab alienare; at ego quoties lubet tuos Auditores omnes a te voco, &amp; ad me traho;</hi> to whom the wiſe phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, <hi>mirum hoc non eſt, tu ſiquidem ad declinem voluptatis tramitem omnes rapis &amp; trahis, ego ad arduum virtutis callem cogo, &amp; impello,</hi> Aelian. <hi>lib.</hi> 13. <hi>de var. hiſt.</hi> Surely in Scripture, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1. hereſie is called a whore,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179829:29"/>
                  <hi>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odo facta eſt meretrix Civitas fidelis;</hi> for even as the ſtrumpet doth eaſily draw to her and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>educeth many, ſo doth hereſie delude, charm and drag men daily to perdition, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and ſin. The ancient Philoſophers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing queſtioned, why there were very many Epicures to be found, but very few peripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teticks or Stoicks; the reaſon they gave, was, that <hi>Stoicorum &amp; Peripateticorum diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplina ſeverior, &amp; ſubtilior erat: Epicureo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum autem laxior, &amp; craſſior.</hi> Hear what <hi>Lactantius lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de divinae Inſtit.</hi> c. 16. ſay, <hi>Epicuri diſciplina multo celebrior ſemper fuit non quia veri aliquid afferat, ſed quia multos ad populare nomen voluptatis, &amp; libertatis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitat: nemo enim non in vitia pronus est, ea<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vincere difficillimum eſt:</hi> and certainly thoſe that become Apoſtates from Chriſt and his Religion, are plung'd by the liberty of their fleſh, and not of any good ſpirit: it's no hard matter to perſwade a voluptuous Religious man, that Prieſts ought to marry, and that it is impoſſible to be chaſte: it's not difficult to perſwade thoſe given to gluttony, that faſtings are ſuperfluous and needleſs, and that drunkenneſs is no ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did not <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> adviſe the King <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. c</hi> to place beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full maids neer the armies of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> that ſo they might be allured to the ſin of the fleſh, and that the women ſhould not at all conſent to give the ſouldiers their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:179829:29"/>will, unleſs they would become Idolaters, <hi>Numb</hi> 31. by which very many <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were deluded and perverted, and this was the only way to overcome them and their Army: what other way or means did <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> uſe for to draw Proſelites after them, then luſt, liberty, avarice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how was <hi>Joannes Fredericus</hi> Duke of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony</hi> brought to be an heretick by <hi>Luther?</hi> it was thus: This Duke had an ambition to bereave the Family of <hi>Auſtria</hi> from being Emperours, which they enjoyed <hi>quaſi jure haereditario;</hi> this his ambition he imparted to <hi>Luther,</hi> who perſwaded the Duke to change his Religion, if he expected a change in the Empire, his helliſh advice was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by the Duke eaſily, being full of envy, and an enemy to <hi>Caeſar;</hi> thus the Duke by the advice of curſed <hi>Luther,</hi> rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an army againſt <hi>Charles the fifth,</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to deſtroy him; but by divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and the brave valour and conduct of the Emperour, the Duke was conquered and taken priſoner, and deprived of being Elector, which place and honour was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> in whoſe Family even to this day it holds: and aſſuredly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but pride, curioſity, an appetite of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, arrogancy, avarice, ambition, uſurpation of ſacred gifts, voluptuouſneſs, an averſion from ſevere diſcipline, luxury,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:179829:30"/>an itching deſire of novelties, and liberty of the fleſh, are the baits that enchaunted your ſoul from the firm ſtanding in the true Church to the ſink of herefie and a poſtaſie. When any falls from Religion, the harm is very dangerous to him that falls, we cannot finde that any of the B. Apoſtles or Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt, nay, nor any of the weaker faithful did fall from their faith by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable Apoſtaſie of <hi>Judas:</hi> which cannot be but a ſignal providence of God towards his faithfull; hereticks imagines, that when any Doctour, preacher, or prieſt of ours runs to apoſtaſy, from us, to their ſect, that then our faith begins to be weakned, and that many more will follow; but this is a very fooliſh conceit, for many reaſons: firſt, becauſe that fall and deficience is no new matter, or unuſual in the Church of Chriſt; whereas in all ages, and times there have been ſome that were permitted to fail, and fall into Apoſtaſie, to the end, that by their deficiency, the Church ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crciſed, but never to fail, or fall away with them; whereas the ſame is not grounded but upon a firm Rock, Chriſt Jeſus: for God almighty when one veſſel is broken can make another, as <hi>Hieremia;</hi> obſerved <hi>c.</hi> 18 did not <hi>Judas</hi> fall off from Chriſt in that time, when he promiſed to draw all things to him? did not immediatly the good thief
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:179829:30"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orn, confeſſe, and believe? though <hi>Peter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>denied</hi> his matter, the <hi>Centurion</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rerted, <hi>revertumur percutientes pectora ſua:</hi> therefore the ruine and fall of members of our Church, doth not at all ſhake our Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or faith. Who in the <hi>Greek</hi> Church was more famous then <hi>Crigines?</hi> Who in the <hi>Latin</hi> Church was more famous then <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>llian?</hi> each of theſe was a moſt antient Doctor in the third age: and at firſt they proved moſt indefatigable and earneſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwers and perſecutors of the Enemies of the Church, hereticks: they were rare Doctors to a great many ſaints, Confeſſors and Martyrs, yet notwithſtanding both fell from the Church into hereſy; and the Church not in the leaſt moved or weakned, for it: did not <hi>Sapricius</hi> in the time of <hi>Valerianus</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, a learned and renowned prieſt (being dragg'd to martirdom for his faith,) denie his faith, and offered ſacrifice to falſe Gods? what ſhall I ſay of <hi>Oſius</hi> the Maſter of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus magnus,</hi> a moſt learned man, and one that was emploied as Legat from the Church, oftentimes; did not he betray, the <hi>Nicene Council,</hi> become an enemy to the true faith, and <hi>an Arian?</hi> yet the Church ſtood perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and triumphant, ſo as when he fell; then the the Enemies of faith, the <hi>Arians</hi> were converted: and what <hi>Oſius</hi> did deny, to wit, the divine ſubſtance in the Son of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:179829:31"/>God, was confeſſed and reſtored, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the <hi>Arians,</hi> ſo as the very Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> did publickly preach avouch, and by publick edicts, did cry down; and cauſed all to be demoliſh'd, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> accurſed <hi>Oſius</hi> with his conſorts did impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly maintain, ſee <hi>Baron. anno.</hi> 357.</p>
               <p>When the Seraphical S. <hi>Francis</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his holy Order was troubled that ſome of his children fell off from thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vocation, and fearing that his Order ſhould fall and decay; hear'd theſe words from Chriſt, why are you troubled <hi>Francis</hi> for ſcandal given by the fall of ſome of your Children? know that when one ſhall turn to their vomit, that I ſhall raiſe another or more in his place. S. <hi>Bonavent. in vita S. Francis.</hi> Much more the Church of Chriſt is to ſtand without interruption. Secondly, becauſe it's no wonder that among ſo many holy, good, and vertuous Chriſtians in the whole Church, there ſhould be one or ſome reprobates: there is not that Community in which may not be found one ſcabby ſheep or other: was not <hi>Cham</hi> a reprobate in the houſe of <hi>Noe?</hi> was not <hi>Iſmael</hi> one in the houſe of <hi>Abraham?</hi> in the houſe <hi>of Iſaac, Eſan?</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Chriſt, Judas?</hi> what wonder therefore can it be that in the Church ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and extended from weſt, to Eaſt; from North, to South, there be found ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:179829:31"/>runagates, and Apoſtates? this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur B. Saviour did often foretell, will the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a want Merchants ships to ſail, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me ſhips are caſt away? will not men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erefore not marry women becauſe ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re found to be ſtrumpets? Thirdly, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe that fals from the true Church do not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll for any real doubt in their faith, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther through their depraved life and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upt behaviour; and for to get more liberty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd freedome of ſinning; and you may reade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <hi>Joan.</hi> 2. <hi>ex nobis prodierunt ſed non erant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x nobis; nam ſi fuiſſent ex nobis permanſiſſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tique nobiſcum:</hi> but now their exorbitant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arriage, their pride, their incorrigibility <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd refractorineſs, their negligence, being weary of a ſpiritual religious life, their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion from penance, and Mortification, <hi>uncupiſcentia carnis oculorum &amp; ſuperbia vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> in effect manifeſt now, that they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot of ours, and becauſe they were not, they went away, becoming Apoſtates: what moved <hi>Origen</hi> to become <hi>an heretick?</hi> as <hi>Vincent. Lyrin. c.</hi> 23. <hi>contra haeres.</hi> writes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut his pride, preſumption of his learning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>magining fooliſhly that he was wiſer then all the world? what cauſed <hi>Jovinianus</hi> to fall? but that he could not endure the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of obedience, and monaſtical life, he was too delicate: ſee S. <hi>Hier. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>contra Jovinian:</hi> therefore becauſe ſuch were
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:179829:32"/>chaff, or ſtubble, no pure clean wheat, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wonder that they were huried away by the winde of temptation; hence S. <hi>Peter, Act.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid <hi>praevaricatus eſt Judas ut abiret in locum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuam:</hi> what was his place, which he expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and was inclined to? was it to hang himſelf, or rather hell, to which, as to his laſt period, or term, he directed his paths and way? God therefore is rather to be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified and praiſed, that he is accuſtomed to purifie and purge his Church from ſuch perverſe putrified members, <hi>ſic pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant peccatores:</hi> ſo as in no way the fall of Prieſts, to become accurſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtats, can derogate any thing from the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, and truth of our faith, but rather doth conduce very much to the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and confirmation of the ſanctity, puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and permanency of the ſame: you may obſerve how the ſea caſts up on the ſhore dead carcaſes, even ſo our Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion vomits up, and caſts out, <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive,</hi> incorrigible, and reprobate dead members: it's moſt certain, that none de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts from our Religion to the Proteſtant revolted Squadron, to the end that he may give himſelf more to prayer, retirements, faſting, mortification, purity of life, and converſation, no ſuch matter; none falls for to forſake and contemn the honors, eaſe, comforts, and pleaſures of the world,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:179829:32"/>neither for to ſhun the ſnares and allurement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f women, nor that he may the more abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate, and renounce his own will, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gne the ſame to the will of his ſuperior: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut rather for the contraty, they run from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that they may enjoy more liberty, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eedom for to follow and purſue their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icked way and cuſtoms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whereas, the Proteſtants ſect received none from us but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eer libertines, reprobate, refractory, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and weak, effeminate ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>caſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever yet any of ſuch infernal Imps has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>een liſted in the catalogue of Saints: <hi>quia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ni ante macellum ſtanti non adjicitur niſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o faeda &amp; mutilis,</hi> even ſo God in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine providence throw none into the devils <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aws, which is hereſy, but only ſuch as are willful reprobats and ſcandalous livers: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore S. <hi>Paul Acts</hi> 20. gives us war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, ſaying, <hi>ego ſcio quoniam post diſceſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em meam intrabunt lupi rapaces in vos non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rcentes gregi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>propter quod vigilate me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oria retinentes,</hi> &amp;c. Sweet <hi>Andrew!</hi> how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame you to be enchanted from the truth of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he revealed principles of the ancient and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oul-ſaving faith of Chriſt, and become an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eretick, which is the ſink of all abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, the moſt horrid and blackeſt ſin that ever was committed? even the Heathen Philoſophers by the only rays of pure Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>res light did abhor ſin, in ſomuch that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristot.</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:179829:33"/>3. <hi>Eth.</hi> ſaid, <hi>melius eſt mori quam faee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re aliquid contra bonum virtutis;</hi> and <hi>Senec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſaid, <hi>Si ſcirem 'Deum ignoſciturum, tamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>care nollem ob p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccati t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rpitudinem:</hi> Did not the great S. <hi>Anſelm</hi> ſay, that if of one ſide he ſaw ſin, and on the other the flames of hell, and if he were to chooſe, he would rather throw himſelf into infernal flames then commit a hainous ſin against God his Maſter, Redeemer, and glorifier and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier: O rare expreſſion! theſe great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers ſeriouſly conſidering the baſe, vile, and abominable nature and malfce of ſin, they could not endure the ſame; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion the nature and malice of hereſie ſurpaſſeth the execration and malice of all imaginable ſins whatſoever: for firſt it draws after it two main puniſhments, and juſt judgements, excecation and induration on man: it blindes and excecates the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, involving it into main darkneſſe of ſundry errours, and withall it indurates, and infatuates the will by wofull pertinacy, whereas faith being the gift of God which hereticks contemn, and willfully reject, by their obſtinate pertinacy, believing ſome points in Scripture that are pleaſing to them, others that diſpleaſes, they will not believe, vainly imagining it to ſuffice, to believe in Chriſt, and that he died for our ſins, though they ſhould believe no more; whence they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:179829:33"/>aſſure themſelves that any man of any Sect, believing in Chriſt, may be in his belief ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; whereas they all have one God and head, Chriſt: O falſe and deluded doctrine! Did not S. <hi>Thomas</hi> deny the article of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection? Did not Chriſt Jeſus require from him and all the faithful, to believe that article as neceſſary for ſalvation? who doubts it? therefore the ſame reaſon muſt follow in all other articles; and why is it neceſſary to believe that Chriſt reſuſcitated, and not that Chriſt's body and bloud is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Sacrament of the Euchariſt? Doth not holy Scripture witneſs this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I ſay, Doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtle <hi>ad Tit.</hi> 3. admoniſh us, <hi>haereticum hominum devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare,</hi> becauſe he is ſubverted and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his own proper judgement; you muſt not reply, that the Apoſtle meant him an heretick that rejects Chriſt, or what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſymbol, for ſo indeed he would not be an heretick, that would reject all the holy Scripture, and all Sacraments; neither alſo he who would condemn marriage and meats, and place two diſtinct perſons in Chriſt: yet ſuch 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. &amp; 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. are held to be hereticks. Thirdly, Did all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity hold, that an heretick could not be ſaved, which moved and excited them vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly always to oppoſe hereticks, confute, ſilence, and condemn them: wherefore has
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:179829:34"/>there been at all times General Councils of Learned Prelats conven'd, from all parts of the inhabitable world, and with great labor and expences celebrated? but for to beat down and confute hereſies, and damn them with <hi>anathema?</hi> why all commerce and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with hereticks forbidden? why very many Roman Catholicks did rather ſuffer exile, loſſe of means, and limbs, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns, then ſubſcribe to here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks? were not all theſe encounters in vain, fooliſhly, and injuriouſly done, if in thoſe ſects of hereſie, ſalvation might be had or obtain'd? The reaſon is, that it would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low by good ilation, that the true Orthodox faith would be no better then the hereſie of <hi>Arians, Pelagians, Neſtorians,</hi> &amp;c. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it's ſtated ſalvation to be had in any of theſe, as well as in the Roman-Catholick Faith, and conſequently it would follow, all thoſe ancient hereticks were ſaved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many of them did hold and beleeve the Apoſtolical Symbol, all which is moſt abſurd; and that any ſhould be ſaved by falſe faith; for falſe faith neither is, nor can be more available for ſalvation then no faith at all: and becauſe the foundation of faith, <hi>viz.</hi> the reaſon of believing, in hereticks is falſe and erroneous; therefore their faith is falſe alſo which depends on falſhood; for they believe their <hi>dogmata</hi> or tenents, either
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:179829:34"/>becauſe their pretended Apoſtles, <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin, &amp;c.</hi> taught them, and theſe could not erre or be deluded, or becauſe by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir own proper ſence and judgement, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agine thoſe to be contained in Scripture, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd this is falſe too; for one man alledges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſame Scripture for this ſect, and another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ledges the very ſame for another different <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct, becauſe they underſtand it not; or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y believe <hi>ſua dogmata,</hi> becauſe ſome are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght interiourly by a private ſpirit of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe of Scipture, &amp; this likewiſe deludes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cauſe for the moſt part all of them do brag <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> boaſt they have the true ſpirit; yet they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch and broaeh contrary things amongſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>emſelves, which verily a good and right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it can never do. Fourthly, as he who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aks one precept, is ſaid and held to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lty of all the precepts, <hi>viz.</hi> if one be an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lterer, that he ſhall be damned, as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e that has committed ſins againſt all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mmandements of God, even ſo in like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ner, whoſoever rejects and will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve one article of true faith, falls from ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on no leſſe then if he had rejected all ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es; wherefore ſome in vain do wiſh or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect that the Church would remit ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g of the articles of faith, to the end it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> come and agree in one with the late <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, but that is impoſſible, for faith can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e neither encreaſe nor decreaſe, <hi>fides ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditamentum
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:179829:35"/>&amp; inciſionem neſcit quia divine</hi> faith is like an hour-clock, her articles a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> made like the teeth of wheels, if you tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> away or pull one tooth, all the fabrick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> machine fails and ſerves for nothing; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thrice happy are the glorious Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> heaven becauſe they have a full viſion a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fruition of the ſweet face of God; bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are the faithfull Chriſtians here beneat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> though pilgrims &amp; travellers, becauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do not ſee God, for by true faith ſhall com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that place where they ſhall ſee God face <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> face for all eternity; and as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 91. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi jam non dicetur nobis; cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d non vides, ſed gaude quia vides;</hi> finiall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if every one might be ſaved in his own fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then we ſhould have no need of recourſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt; it were enough ſome to be ſent b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God that would preach the knowledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one God, according to the Apoſtle, <hi>ad G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2. <hi>Si per legem juſtitia, ergo gratis Chriſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtuus eſt:</hi> and withall the very Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> would prove falſe and in vain, which te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> us Chant to be our Redeemer and Medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour, through whoſe ſacred bloud we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cleanſed, through whoſe faith we ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be juſified, and in whoſe only Name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ought to be ſaved; for then, if this we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> true, and that any one, in any faith may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaved, then every humane faith and perſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion would have been ſufficient for ſalvat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:179829:35"/>for the Turks, though they beleeve in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e God, Creator and Remunerator of all, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et they do not beleeve by any divine faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t becauſe <hi>Mahomet</hi> delivered it ſo in his <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>coran,</hi> in which many mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t falſe things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e taught, as that <hi>Mahomet</hi> was the prophet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So likewiſe the Jews, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey beleeve, they beleeve becauſe their <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bbins</hi> do expound the Scriptures ſo to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em; yet notwithſtanding all their grounds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vain, falſe, and moſt erroneous, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Rule of their faith is mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t falſe. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain reaſon that moves ſome to ſay, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y may be ſaved in his faith, is, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d it incredible, that all Jews and Turks, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which very many do piouſly worſhip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, and live innocently and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>noxiouſly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould eternally periſh, and that only for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t beleeving in Chriſt; for this they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eade an excuſe, by reaſon from their cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e they were otherwiſe inſtructed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d according to their light and breeding, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d in what they could ſerve God, therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e gates of heaven muſt not be made ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w, as that that vaſt number ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uded and not enter in, but all this ſignifies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thing; for if it is not incredible, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od hath left for ſo many thouſand years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the world (the Jews only excepted) in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e darkneſſe of Idolatry, wherein for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>in they peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hed; ſo it is very eaſie for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:179829:36"/>one to perſwade himſelf, the ſame t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have happened to the Jews and Turks; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> further, the Jews and Turks now-aday<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have leſſe plea to excuſe them in not belie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Chriſt then the Ethnicks had in an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times, whereas the Jews and Turk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> could ſeek and learn from the Chriſtians li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving amongſt them the true faith of Chriſt which the <hi>Ethincks</hi> could not do, becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they lived in darkneſs, and were hurried a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>way by the common Cuſtome, to follo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and obſerve the Religion of their Anceſtors To conclude, I ſay, that if there may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> found ſome that never heard a word o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſts Religion neither have had any kind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of impulſes for to inquire and embrace th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſame, ſuch ſhall not be damned for infidel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if none ſuch ſins they have committed either they will be illuminated by God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that they come to the knowledge of ſaving faith, or if they die in their natural innocen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, they ſhall incurr only the <hi>poena damn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> not of ſenſe, in the other world. If a prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant living and dying ſo, if he die in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſtate of innocency he ſhall enter into heave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> becauſe baptized in Chriſt. O <hi>Andrew</hi> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to your bleeding Mother, ſhe is you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true Mother! while you remain abroa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the harlot you can have no quietneſs no comfort, no grace, no eaſe, no refreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no food but husks, being deſtitute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:179829:36"/>the help of the Sacraments, which are the heavenly conduits through ſuch divine grace is conveyed to Drooping ſouls, you are deſtitute of the true Word of God, of the prayers of the Church, the Congregation of faithful Chriſtians, you are deſtitute of good and laudable examples: you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of a dread ſacrifice, deſtitute of faith, deſtitute of Religion: you have loſt all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, all Mortification, and even the fear of a living God: conſider your lamentable ſtate, you are become one of a Sect, where there is no Guide, Rule or Judge or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which God hath appointed for your direction, and to teach and continue true faith in the world: the Guide, Rule, Judge, and Authority which Roman Catholicks follow, is ſuch, and the ſame in effect is which the firſt Chriſtians follow'd in the time of the Apoſtles, and in every reſpect, able and ſufficient to execute its function, and indeed the only means imaginable, not only to teach and convey true faith, unto the world, but alſo to reconcile all differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ariſing in matters of faith, as alſo to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince &amp; condemn all hereticks &amp; ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, &amp; ſo eſtabliſh that union that becoms the Church of God, which Chriſt Jeſus our all-wiſe Legiſlator hath ſetled in the world; and this Guide, and Judge which Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick do follow, is infallible, and hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:179829:37"/>credentials from heaven to prove her ſelf to be ſo, conſequently that we are all obliged to captivate our underſtanding to the obedience of Faith.</p>
               <lg>
                  <head>Adhortatio Paranetica ad Sacrilegum Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatam Caſſellenſem.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Salve Andrea, &amp; me tantisper accipe?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A roaring Lion, by Chriſts moſt heavenly call,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>From</hi> Saul <hi>became a Gospel preaching</hi> Paul;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou</hi> Sall <hi>from Prieſt, and preaching childe of</hi> Paul,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beguil'd, art turn'd to be a black curs'd</hi> Saul;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your proud w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll ſhak'd off the yoke of Faith,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Purſuing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>an n'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> lies, illuſions and deceit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lord! what's caitiff fleſh when left to it ſelf?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faith needs muſt wreck when m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n is his own ſhelf.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How vain is humane confidence, how frail?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Only Faiths true ways can our ſouls avail.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vae impio in malum retributio manuum ejus fiet ei.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Iſa. 3.</bibl>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Who cannot, Sir, but ſtand amazed and ſtartle at your diſmal fall from the true anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church of Chriſt? you a profeſſor of Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty (though of no ſolid intenſive learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,) a Religious prieſt of a Society moſt renown'd for learning, ſanctity, piety, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and bleſſings, you a preacher of the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:179829:37"/>word and pennance; you who cleav'd ſo faſt to the Rock, Chriſt, now to be ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, and ſo ſuddenly, by the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubtil wiles, cunning, crafty ſlight, and ſophiſtry of craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeducers, hurried away to a Religion falſe, tracherous, and deſtructive of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and metamorphoſed into the likeneſs of a loathſome and deformed villain, and now in your old age become like a childe, againſt that wholſome advice of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>nolite pueri effici ſenſibus,</hi> children commonly never regards precious things; carts, coaches, and wheels made of earth, delights them more then the rich brave painted coaches of Kings, of great State and magnificence, for theſe little ones are only led by their ſences; as you ſhall ſee a childe break to peices books of high eſteem, and value, throw away precious gems and moſt noble Jewells, and take up a black coal, kiſs it, and eat it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch a little childe, you <hi>Andrew Sall,</hi> is become of late, when you made choiſe of darkneſs for light, black coals of hereſie, apoſtaſie, liberty, illuſions, falſhood and ſordid ways, and ſuch as pleaſe your wretched blinde ſences, and ſhamefully condemn moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, moſt precious and moſt ſoveraign things, as true un-erring faith, Religion, glorious vertues, Sanctity, grace, mortification, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of life and converſation, devotion, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:179829:38"/>prayers, contemplation, and ſweet retirement, all which are leading to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal glory. O ſtark blindneſs! <hi>hinc lacrimae!</hi> this wretched exchange ſure muſt proceed from very groſs ignorance, pride and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs: for the mind of man being the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt among rational natures addicted to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and carnal actions, apprehends no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing perfectly, beſide ſenſible, external, temporal things; as honour, riches, voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, pleaſures, contentments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and cannot apprehend ſpiritual and heavenly things, <hi>viz.</hi> the beauty of vertue, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and ſweet enjoyments of eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, the beatifical viſion and fruition of Gods moſt glorious face, the onely ſource of ful content, and never-ending felicity; I ſay, theſe things they apprehend but very weakly, and even in a confus'd and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing manner; whereas the affection of the will ſtill follows ſtrongly, the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion; as when a man doth taſte of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding ſweetneſs of terreſtriall happineſs, he vainly imagines the ſame to be far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then really it is, even ſo when one taſtes a little of the roughneſs, difficulty, and loathſome bitterneſs of vertue, doth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe fondly imagine the ſame to be more craggy, intollerable, and loathſome then truly it is, and ſo falls back and deſiſts from going forward in the queſt &amp; happy purſuit
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:179829:38"/>of ſolid vertue. O <hi>Andrew! non erit tibi am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius infans dierum &amp; ſenex qui non impleat dies ſuos quoniam puer centum annorum mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etur,</hi> Iſa. 65. that is to ſay, if any old man be found of childiſh behaviour and becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>puer centum annorum,</hi> and yet would prove a childe in his ſenſes, in a vicious life and converſation, that man ſhall not perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in the Militant, to paſs to the Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Church, but ſhall be precipitated into everlaſting darkneſs and flames: oh <hi>Andrea! haec te horrenda terreant,</hi> how come you in your old age to be ſo enchanted, and ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably to revolt from a true antiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Faith? how come you to fly wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly from Religion, piety, pennance, and auſterity of life? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but becauſe you doted; you proved <hi>puer centum anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> becoming a ſcandalous Apoſtate, a vile proteſtant, and a pittifull object of ſcorn to boys and lackeys: ſo as you may ſay with King <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Reg. vivit Dominus quoniam filius mortis eſt qui hoc f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cit:</hi> The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Philoſophers were accuſtomed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare weak effeminate men, who eaſily would part with ſome moſt precious thing for a bubble or trifle, to a fiſh, call'd, <hi>polype,</hi> which cleaves ſo faſt to a rock that it will be ſooner pulled into peeces, then let go its gripe; yet according to <hi>Pierius valer. lib.</hi> 25. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. when a little ſweet water is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:179829:39"/>poured down upon it, then immediately he will let looſe what he kept faſt. O pittiful <hi>Andrew,</hi> did not you of late, by your <hi>ſubita diſſeſſio</hi> prove like this fiſh: who could ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin that you ſhould be ſo enchanted as to let go your faſt gripe, and forſake your ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſo amorous, ſo obliging and ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious maſter, ſaviour and benefactour? O execration! O blindneſs! O execration the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t black that ever the ſun look'd on! how could ſuch folly and madneſs creep into your brain? oh <hi>aqua dulcis!</hi> the perfum'd ſweet water of <hi>Camas</hi> was taſted by you, poor <hi>Anarew,</hi> by which you became miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably intoxicated, amus'd, charm'd, and quite undone: <hi>confregiſti jugum, rupiſti vincula, dixiſti non ſerviam, Jer.</hi> 2. lo, the ſad effects of your <hi>aqua aulcis,</hi> conferring, eating, drinking, ſporting with Arch-hereticks againſt the expreſs will of your Superiours, at <hi>Camas,</hi> you expos'd your ſelf willfully to the imminent danger of being enſnar'd by dangerous ſoul-hunters and fowlers: alas! <hi>Inventi ſunt in populo i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pii inſidiantes quaſi aucupes, laqueos ponentes &amp; pedicas ad capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endos viros:</hi> ſure you met with a dextrous fowler at <hi>Camas</hi> who by fair language, ſweet plauſible inſinuations, darting at your weak ſimple heart, beams of great promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and allurements of full content, gold, liberty, pleaſure, promotion to ſmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ky ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:179829:39"/>making uſe in a moſt dextrous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſubtil and crafty methods of deluding you, ſtruck through your wavering and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſoul, with <hi>aqua dulcis</hi> which has been your bane, bringing you to feed you ſelf and others with falſe appearances inſtead of truth, and brand you with a perpetual blot of infamy to all proſterity, and fix an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting guilt upon your ſoul; and your now liberty the <hi>Meteor</hi> which by glittering brightneſs of deceitfull light, dazles your eys, unwarily; and like a wandring fire miſleads you in your ſearch for true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, through the blind paths of Apoſtaſy, ignorance and folly; drawing yet into the dangerous precipices of all impiety and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy, <hi>de ſcelere ad ſcelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> What falſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance ſoever of content at pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ent this way holds forth to your deluded minde, <hi>vae impio in malum,</hi> &amp;c. Oh <hi>Andrew!</hi> how come you to prove like the clouds, which obſcures the ſun that raiſed them? take this gerogliphick, and conſider, how when the ſun doth ſpread her radiant beams, chaſing darkneſs from the face of the earth, which dark clouds, envying (as it were) at ſo bright light, they begin to endeavour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tre the beauty and reſplendency thereof: what are the clouds, but groſs earthly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours raiſed by the rays of the ſun up to the ſuperiour Region, where they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſed
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:179829:40"/>and made dark clouds, and yet they obfuſcate and endeavour to endarken their maker; O ingratitude! thus you ungratfull wretch, do begin to wage war with God your maker and infinite benefactor; who raiſed you <hi>Andrew Sall</hi> from nothing, to great honour and dignity, as to be a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, a prieſt, a legat, a ſtar, a guide, a phiſitian of ſouls? and what is it that you return to his divine majeſty for all thoſe bleſſings and favours? oh! is it to bandy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him and uſe his bleſſings for to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor his holy name? is it to war furiouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his faith; to make him a lyar in your pulpit, by your lyes and forgeries? your malicious crying down the pape, prayers to Saints, the real preſence, and your lowd bawling up creeping Proteſtaniſme? O in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude and madneſs! to rip up the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells of your mother, his ſpouſe, the Roman Catholick Church, calling her whore, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is this your gratitude? ah poor <hi>Andrew!</hi> all your bawlings and railings recoiles upon your own ſelf, <hi>quid prudentis eſt? cum poſſit nolle nocere; quid ſtulti proprium? non poſſe, &amp; velle nocere.</hi> you are not able to annoy or beat down the glory and luſtre of the Catholick Church, nor impede the glorious trophies and daily mervelous growth thereof: know that Chriſt is ſtill at hand for to defend his flock
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:179829:40"/>and Church from the venom of Apoſtats; his eyes are fix'd on them, alwaies ready to beat down and deſtroy all ariſing Enemies: what became of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate, for attempting to perſecute the true Church? all the world knows it: what became of <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> &amp;c. and of all the reſt of your curſed fellow-laborers in the totter'd ſilveſtrial vineyard of proteſtaniſme? <hi>Flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundus</hi> will tell you, they all came to a moſt wofull and execrable end; <hi>haec te tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menda moveant, terreant<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Andrea?</hi> Reclaim therefore in time <hi>Andrew,</hi> begin to make a ſpeedy retreat, open your eyes veiled with a fatal ſcarf of impudency; ſhut not the eyes of your underſtanding againſt the pure heavenly ways of Gods true doctrine for your ſalvation? imitate that brave <hi>Avicena,</hi> a man of a moſt ſuper-excellent wit, yet by unhappineſs of birth rank'd in the infernal Sect of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> coming to conſider, how his falſe prophet had placed the beatitude of the life to come, in ſenſuall pleaſures and contentments of the body, was aſham'd of it, and ſo ſhurnk from his prophet, that he might not betray his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; the laws <hi>Mahomet</hi> gave, did conſider beatitude and miſery, only within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of the body: Oh <hi>Andrew!</hi> forſake your proteſtant Sect, which (as you well know in your Conſcience) doth place all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:179829:41"/>in the pleaſures honors, liberty and contentments of the body, and obſtructs all means and ways to vertue, to ſanctity, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, mortification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and doth ſtifle the fear of a living and dreadfull God: Oh <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew!</hi> do not betray your Reaſon, nor your conſcience, ſhrink away from your darkneſs and apoſtaſie? reclame and be converted, like a great Pollititian lately by this <hi>Dilem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi> Either there is a living God, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Judgment after this periſhable life or no: if there be none ſuch, yet if I believe that there is, it cannot prejudice me at all, but it will rather very much avail me, for it will move me to embrace an honeſt moral Chriſtian like life; if there be, and yet I ſhall not believe it, rather flatly deny any ſuch thing, what infinitly great torments and flames muſt I expect for this my perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſneſs, blaſphemy, and horrid contempt: Further, either there are rewards for good works of the Juſt and Vertuous after this life or no? and likewiſe if exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be prepared for the impious by God, (as by the light of nature we may without queſtion believe) or no? If there be none at all, yet to believe, hope and fear ſuch a thing, cannot hurt me, but rather forward me to the practiſe of vertue and honeſty, <hi>&amp;c</hi> and if there are really ſuch to be expected, and that I ſhall not believe it, and ſo live
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:179829:41"/>wickedly and licentiouſly, what other can be expected but eternal flames among the damned? The Almighty, <hi>Andrew,</hi> illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate your underſtanding, and inflame your heart for to renounce your carnal childiſh ſences, and to turn your ſelf to your mother, the Roman Catholick Church, wherein only is true faith, Religion, grace and true comfort to be found: <hi>opus annorum multorum perdidiſti;</hi> ariſe, and rouſe from your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Apoſtaſy;</p>
               <div type="addendum">
                  <head>An Appendix.</head>
                  <p>IN the great and moſt important affairs of faith all, on all ſides, agree, that they are bound on pain of damnation to believe all truths ſufficiently propounded to them, as revealed of God, and to obey and ſubmit to that Guide, Rule, Judge and Authority which God hath inſtituted and appointed to teach and govern them; the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe whoſoever denies any thing ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently propounded to be revealed by God, denies Gods veracity, and makes him a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar. No proteſtant can ſhew any other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why by denying the Trinity, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or the Incarnation, Gods veracity is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, and God thereby made a liar, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Trinity and Incarnation are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently propounded as divine Revelations;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:179829:42"/>therefore the Real Preſence, prayer to Saints, the Papes Supremacy, auricular confeſſion, purgatory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being without doubt as ſufficiently propounded in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture as thoſe myſteries of the Trinity and Incarnation; by denying which Gods Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity muſt be alſo denied, and ſo God made a lyar. See in <hi>chap.</hi> 16.12. <hi>when the spirit of Truth is come, he will guide you into all truth:</hi> but all truth excludes all errours, and this for ever, which was to be longer then the Apoſtles were to live. If you <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> enquire, by what means this teaching ſhall be, by whom all people ſhall be taught, all truths, and ſhall be preſerved from all errours? S. <hi>Paul</hi> will tell you, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. <hi>He gave ſome Apoſtles</hi> (ſucceeding in full Apoſtolical authority) <hi>ſome Prophets</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounders of the prophets) <hi>ſome Evangeliſts</hi> (preachers of the Goſpel) <hi>ſome Paſtors and Teachers,</hi> to what end? <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt:</hi> for what time or how long? <hi>till we all come in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> now <hi>Andrew</hi> you may ask, will theſe ſecure us? the very next verſe tells you, <hi>that henceforth we be no more children, toſſed to and fro with every winde of doctrine, by the ſlieght of men and cunning craftineſſe, whereby they lie in wait to deceive,</hi> as you lately have been moſt ſhamefully by the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:179829:42"/>ſlieghts of Satan and his Inſtruments, pride, luſt, and avarice, hurried away from Chriſts unerring Church, wherein only are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſeen unfeigned miracles, ſanctity of life, efficacy of doctrine, admirable repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of ſinners, converſions of people and Nations, unity, ſtability, perpetuity, uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted ſucceſſion of lawfull paſtors, which cannot be found in your proteſtant ſect; theſe are ſuch heavenly marks as are impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for God to affix unto a lie, which is as impoſſible, as to ſet his hand and ſeal to the confirmation of falſhood; according to the Rule of <hi>Gamaliel; If it be of God it will hold:</hi> the faith of Roman-Catholicks holds, and daily grows more numerous in her proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, when the unſteady wavering prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant pitiful ſect daily changes, like the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melion, from one falſe doctrine to another; which occaſioned the moſt illuſtrious Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe <hi>Badenſis</hi> from a <hi>Lutheran</hi> to become a Roman-Catholick: the ſame inſtability of hereticks, ſcoffed and laugh'd at by <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericus</hi> great Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> at a time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing queſtioned by a familiar friend, what did his <hi>Lutherans</hi> believe? he anſwered, <hi>quid hoc anno credunt ſcio, quid vero credituri ſint anno ſequenti neſcio, nec ipſimet ſciunt:</hi> no wonder having loſt their ground, their rule, their un-erring Judge, the Roman-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church: ſome years paſt the proteſtants
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:179829:43"/>in <hi>England,</hi> according to their firſt inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did obſerve the Lent exactly, and alſo were accuſtomed to faſt from meat on Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days &amp; Saturdays, but alas! all that is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorten, all is chang'd, nothing permanent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them but perſecution of the Roman-Catholicks: yet to obſerve the Lent, and to abſtain from meat the forty days of Lent, &amp; withal on Frydays and Saturdays, would much conduce to the weal-publick for the growth of cattle, and for the comfort of poor people, meat being ſo exceſſive dear for not obſerving the faſts on thoſe holy times: not ſpeaking of the infinite comfort and encrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of bleſſings, both to ſoul and body, which daily accrew to Kingdoms where the Lent, and Frydays and Saturdays are duely obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and faſted in the Roman-Cath. Church. Now <hi>Andrew,</hi> I conjure you in the bowels of Charity, to learn by heart that moſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly leſſon of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>viz. Learn of me, for I am meek and humble of heart;</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to this remember S. <hi>John</hi> 4.6. <hi>We are of God, He that heareth God, heareth us, he that is not of God, heareth us not, hereby know we the spirit of truth and the ſpirit of errour: Andrew!</hi> nothing was required to diſtinguiſh thoſe two ſpirits, but to hear or to refuſe to hear the Apoſtolical Teachers: Lo, S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Faith comes by hearing;</hi> it will be as neceſſary now for you to hear in theſe our
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:179829:43"/>times thoſe that are lawfully commiſſioned to teach, as it was in the time of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: Come along therefore, return to your Mother, your true un erring guide; fly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſave your ſoul, begin to curſe the day that you began to curſe and diſhonour your true Mother, in imitation of that great Hereſiarch <hi>Calvin,</hi> who, conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with intolerable ſtench from vermine, cryed out aloud, ſaying, <hi>Maledicta dies qnae primum ſtudio &amp; ſcriptioni falſae me adduxit:</hi> Bolſecus <hi>in vita Calvini, haec te horrenda mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veant &amp; terreant,</hi> from appearing againſt truth and the faith of Chriſt, for vain often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, for ſordid gain, for to pleaſe men, and diſpleaſe the all-ſeeing God.</p>
                  <p>O <hi>Andrew!</hi> how come you to forſake your true mother the Roman-Catholick Church (which is the womb of your begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and boſome of your repoſe) and fall into the cruel hands of a falſe mother and harlot? I pray obſerve 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> how two har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots came to <hi>Solomon</hi> for to decide the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie between them about a living child the one alledging it was hers, and the other alſo alledging the childe belonged to her; the King ſaid, bring me a ſword, and they brought a ſword before the King, and the King ſaid, divide the living childe in two, and give half to one and half to the other: then ſpake the woman whoſe the living
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:179829:44"/>childe was (for her bowels yerned toward her ſon) ſaying, O my Lord, give her the living childe, and in no wiſe ſlay it, but the other, the falſe mother ſaid, let it not be mine or thine, but divide it; then the King out of his wiſedom ſaid, give her the childe, ſlay it not, ſhe is mother thereof, becauſe ſhe has true love to her childe, and will not have it divided: your ſoul is a childe which is claim'd by two Mothers, the Roman-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Chhrch, and the pretended Church of Proteſtants; how ſhall we finde out the true mother from the falſe one? by <hi>Solomons dividatur infans,</hi> let the childe be divided in two; the Roman-Catholick Church cannot endure diviſion; the ſoul muſt not be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, it muſt cleave altogether to the true Mother-Church, Chriſt's ſpouſe, the houſe and temple of God, the pillar and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Truth: it muſt believe all the Seven Sacraments, all articles of faith, believe all tenents and revealed myſteries propounded as means for ſalvation; with S. <hi>Paul we cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate our underſtandings to the obedience</hi> of her true and un-errable faith; but the falſe Mother will have the ſoul divided in two, ſhe is for diviſion and for halfs, ſeeking to bring into the houſe of God an anarchy of the children of <hi>Belial,</hi> a diviſion, a deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of union and of Monarchical heavenly Government, <hi>diuidatur infans<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:179829:44"/>ſay, they have faith, but will have no works of faſting, watching, praying, pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, nor mortification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they beleeve that their laick Miniſter doth aboliſh origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſin in baptiſm, but will not beleeve that Chriſt left power to true and lawful prieſts to abſolve from actual mortal ſins; they will have the Lords Supper, but will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Chriſt's words, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c eſt corpus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>cum;</hi> the reality of his body in a moſt miraculous manner in the Euchariſt; they will follow Scripture, but only what is pleaſing to them, and what is contradictory to fleſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled appetites they do reject and deny: theſe words <hi>per ſolam fidem,</hi> by bare faith you are ſaved, are welcome to them, but good works, maceration of the body, and auſterity of life they cannot endure: <hi>ereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite &amp; multiplicabini</hi> pleaſes them, <hi>ſerviti ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ri &amp; libidini,</hi> &amp;c. but other words of Scripture they will not li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ten to, as, <hi>fides ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne operibus eſt mortua, poenitentiam agite; ſic luceat lux veſtra ut videat opera veſtra bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na; Regnum coelorum vim patitur &amp; vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenti r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>piunt illud; caſtigo corpus m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um, &amp; ad implco in carne mea ea quae deſunt paſſioni Chriſti;</hi> theſe places of Scripture they will not follow; Is not this to divide the childe? <hi>dividatur infans:</hi> they are altogether for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and confuſion; they have Churches, but without lawful prieſts; altars, without
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:179829:45"/>ſacrifice and religion: every religion either true or falſe, in all ages, had always a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as a proteſtative ſigne of acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of divine excellency and ſupreme ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: In the Law of nature, from the very beginning, we finde ſacrifice begun by <hi>Abel.</hi> which after continued by the Patriarchs, <hi>Noe, Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob;</hi> In the written Law ſo many ſacrifices according to <hi>Leviticus,</hi> and if we look upon Idolaters, the Gentiles, we ſhall finde them given to many different ſacrifices, ſo as a ſacrifice is inſeparable from the law, according to S. <hi>Paul, Heb.</hi> 7. ſaying, <hi>Tranſlato Sacerdotio ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt ut &amp; leg is tranſlatio fiat;</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid <hi>that Prieſthood being removed or tranſlated, the law of neceſſity muſt be removed;</hi> if prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood be aboliſh'd, the law likewiſe muſt be, for to every law or religion, ſacrifice and prieſthood is connatural, intrinſecal, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable, being correlatives; for prieſthood is in order to ſacrifice eſtabliſh'd, and the law is ordained in order to ſacrifice and prieſthood, delivering precepts and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies relating to prieſthood; <hi>tranſlato ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotio,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>dividatur infans:</hi> the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants they have our temples, but al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s! bare walls; no prieſts, no sacrifice; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no law or religion; therefore <hi>qui ſine le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge viv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt, ſine lege peribunt;</hi> they have ſheep without paſtors, paſtors without miſſion,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:179829:45"/>function, order, conſecration, character, or true commiſſion; Chriſtians without grace by hand impoſition, prophets without mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, faith without works, and charity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out effects: behold <hi>Sall,</hi> excellent peeces, (forſooth) of a reformed Church to which you adhere; you ſee all is but diviſion and ſubdiviſion; you ſeparated your ſelf from the Catholick Church which acknowledgeth a viſible head, an univerſal Paſtor, Vice ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of Chriſt on earth, eſtabliſhed by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words of Jeſus Chriſt in S. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.17, 18, 19. averred by all the holy Fathers, confeſſed by the continuation of a lawfull ſucceſſion, in the revolution of ſo many ages, without any interruption: and <hi>Sall</hi> muſt blindely divorce and ſeparate himſelf from it, withſtanding the force of Gods ſpirit: what will <hi>Sall</hi> be able to alledge in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at the dreadful Judgement that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects him? ah! he will ſay, that he thought the proteſtant was the true and lawfull Church: Miſerable wretch! ſeeſt thou not that the memory of all ages, the conſent of all Nations, the very ancient ſtones of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples beſpeak thy damnation? what miracles haſt thou ſeen or ever heard of wrought to this day among proteſtants? what Angel hath ſpoken to thee to remove to them? what ſanctity and holineſſe of life haſt thou noted in the authours of this ſect, or in their
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:179829:46"/>deluded proſelites? wert thou <hi>Andrew</hi> ſo bereav'd of humane underſtanding, as not to ſee palpably, that a pretended Religion which begun by breach of promiſes made to God, by the ſacriledges and impurities of Apoſtates, by a general revolt againſt God, againſt King, againſt divine and humane laws, by the liberty, filth, and ordure of the carrion the fleſh, by the diſſolution of good manners, by bloud, tyranny and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, could take its ſource from the holy Ghoſt? didſt thou not ſet before thy eyes the deſolations of thy poor countrey, the robbing and prophaning of Churches, Gods houſes, and the ruine and impoveriſhings of thouſands of brave ancient Families, to take thence, and from no other their ſource and origin? Oh but you will ſay, I found that this ſect had the Scripture of its ſide: ah la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable illuſion! to whom <hi>Sall</hi> did the Scripture ſend thee if not to the prieſts and lawful Paſtors? what ſaid the Scripture, but that thou oughteſt to keep the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thou oughteſt to obey the Church and Prelats; thou oughteſt not to truſt thine own judgement, thou oughteſt to captivate thy underſtanding in matters of faith, and that it is better to beleeve with a holy ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity then as you do, and queſtion with a proud, peremptory, and vain curioſity? could'ſt thou be ignorant that the devils and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:179829:46"/>all damn'd hereticks had taken the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of Scripture only to colour their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, malice and apoſtaſie, and that with paſſages which had a fairer ſhew and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance then thoſe now of thy deluded delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Miniſters? and yet all that followed them are miſerably damn'd, and ſo are you vile varlet, unleſſe you ſound a timely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, freely confeſſing you have erred as man, and proteſt you will not perſevere in apoſtaſie, miſchief, and rebellion from the Church, the womb of your beginning, and boſome of your repoſe: Open thine eyes, poor beguiled <hi>Andrew,</hi> at leaſt to the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and heavy judgements of God which thou haſt ſo long ſhut to thy duty, conſider that the laſt verdict and ſentence of thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy ſect is already written in heaven, and that it muſt ſoon yield and fall to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as other blinde hereſies have done: what can hinder you <hi>Sall</hi> from returning to the boſom of the Roman-Catholick Church, which ceaſeth not to ſtretch her arms and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen her heart to your obedience and humble ſubmiſsion? are you afraid that Infidels will blame you of inconſtancy in changing of your Religion? know you not that there is only ſin, vice, and errour to which you muſt want conſtancy? why ſhould you bluſh at humane weakneſs, and not at withſtanding and denying truth? was it a blemiſh to S.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:179829:47"/>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> to become an Apoſtle of a cruel perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor? was it a ſhame to <hi>Constantine the Great</hi> of a heatheniſh Infidel to become a Chriſtian? was it a blemiſh to <hi>Clouis</hi> the firſt King of <hi>France</hi> to be drawn to Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by a woman? Finally, was it a ſhame to very many noble, learned proteſtant Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and very many perſons of quality, who daily return to the Roman-Catholick Religion? let us impute the many falls that happens, to the malice of the devil, and to the age we live in, and to the weakneſſe of corrupt nature, but let us not grudge God the converſion of ſouls, which are the works of his hands: do not follow the courſe of the times, rather follow the light of your conſcience: what matters it if the children of darkneſſe, <hi>viz.</hi> proteſtants, judge ill of the children of light? Did ever the Sun bluſh for not being look'd upon wiſhfully by blinde owls and bats? who can juſtly blame you for having ſubmitted wilful ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy to moderation, to truth, to vertue, to ways of grace, peace and ſanctity? hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane judgement to divine law, and for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving followed rather infinite learned, holy, and conſciencious brave men of all ages, then a handful of proud, unwarrantable, ignorant, rebellious and ſelf-ſeeking ſpirits, that have no other Religion but back and belly, becauſe they have moulded their
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:179829:47"/>ſouls meerly of fleſh and bloud? we men have above brute beaſts the reſurrection of the body; we have above the devils, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to cry for mercy, to reclame and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge we are ſinners: Is it poſſible that the ſweet alluring, though deluding commodities and gilded pleaſures of this fading world, and temporall bleſsings, ſhall as yet keep you back from returning? what can you hope more of this ſect forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by God and men, though it ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe unto you mountains of gold? ought you peradventure for a falſe and deceitfull repreſentation of honours, goods, riches or momentany pleaſures, to yield and deliver your ſoul to eternal pains, and render your name and memory hateful to all men living? Let not ſo great an illuſion creep into your brain, now in the confuſion and low ebb of reeling Proteſtancy: God means to ſever the chaff from the good corn, to part true children from the unlawful and baſe born; the fire is kindled to try the brethren of gold and lead; faith is tried and ſealed with the ſignet of tribulation, perſecution and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; forſake the ſpirit of Satan which breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in you the ſpirit of errour, lies, crimes, diſorders, frantick fancies, and fool-hardy conceits: yeeld, yeeld, <hi>Sall,</hi> ſeek as much as you can, your glory in humility; obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſubmiſsion of ſpirit to lawful pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:179829:48"/>and be ſure that there and no where elſe is the only holy way to truth, faith, religion, and ſalvation: In the name of God weigh at leiſure theſe conſiderations of this Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign antidote; kick no longer againſt the goad; go no more to forge difficulties and illuſions; you ſhall no ſooner ſet your foot in the ſheep-fold of the true Catholick Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, with ſo many men of great note lately and daily converted (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all penal Statutes, Proclamations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſations, mulcts, ſequeſtrations) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but all phantaſies will vaniſh, you ſhall live in peace of conſcience, and receive grace to your ſoul. But alas! I am afraid that it is now adays eaſier to bring to the ſheepfold of Chriſt whole entire Provinces and Cities, then to convert one perverſe obſtinate here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick: The Athieſts are converted, not by force of arms or compulſion, but by the preaching of the pure word of God, by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles and vertuous examples of Roman-Catholicks; but a perverſe heretick is more pertinacious, becauſe more preſumptuous; neither by ſound arguments, nor by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, nor conviction of the underſtanding, can be removed from his liberty of hereſie; See what S. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſays, <hi>Facilius eſt furori Gentilium occurrere raptiſque populos abeſtiali ſcientia ad fidei pietatem praedicando converte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quam quemlibet haereticum in ſui perfidia
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:179829:48"/>dogmatis confidentem, ad fidem rectam revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care.</hi> This glorious Doctor ſays, that it is more facil to cure and reſtore to his ſight one that is ſtark blinde, having his eyes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up and not open, then one that hath his eyes open, and yet can ſee nothing; his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe he that hath eyes cloſe needs no more then to open up his eyes, <hi>applican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do activa paſſivus;</hi> even ſo it is with you <hi>Andrew:</hi> you have your eyes open, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt, in the Scriptures, and that there is a heaven, and hell, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet you cannot nor will not look attentively, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be convinced, neither by reaſon, miracles, nor yet by the heroick brave ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Roman Catholicks: you are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, you are like an owl that cannot ſee at noon-day the Goſpel: O excecation! O purblind execration! <hi>vae impio in malum,</hi> I believe I may be cenſured by ſome and thought to be too ſevere and ſharp in this my expreſſion deſigned onely for to recover you a loſt ſheep from the gall of bitterneſs and bond of iniquity; but let me tell you, that publick ſcandall muſt have publick and ſevere reprehenſions to prevent utter ruine and perdition, both my zeal and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall ever expreſs it ſelf both ways a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any that gives ſcandal to Chriſts flock, I am inſtructed to be rough by my ſweet Jeſus, who never was ſo invective againſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:179829:49"/>any, as the Scribes and Phariſees, the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites of that age, and truly theſe my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions are not ſo ſharp out of any end but to ſhew you, <hi>Andrew,</hi> your own guilt in order to your ſpeedy reviviſcence and repentance; ſuch diſeaſes as feſters inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly requires a faithfull, though rough hand to ſearch them, and to keep from gran-green: he that is fallen into a deep ſleep of hereſie, muſt have loud cryes to awaken and rouſe him: I deſire you therefore to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve <hi>vincula colli tui? cumputruisti enim in oculis tuis placens tibi &amp; placere cupiens oculis perditorum hominum, ſuperbe derilantium in quorum ore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aquei diaboli:</hi> fly from them <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew, abhorre ea quae te praeparant ad interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; appete ea nunc quae te foelicem perpetuo facere poſſunt:</hi> Learn from S. <hi>Paul, Non cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere omni ſpiritui.</hi> Learn from <hi>Solomon, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos amicos unum autem habere conciliarium:</hi> Learn from Chriſt, <hi>Domum tuam ſupra Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram fundare:</hi> Learn from the Apoſtles to ſail within that ſacred Ship the Catholick Church, which can never be caſt on rocks or errours, to ſuffer ſhipwrack; <hi>ad hanc a te turpiter derelictam Eccleſiam ut redeas, ego admoneo &amp; exhortor gemebundus ne pernitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis ſeductorum, &amp; ſeducentium hominum voci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus temere credas, ne pro luce tenebras, pro die noctem, pro cibo famem, pro remedio vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num pro vitae mortem ſumas? Andrew,</hi> call
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:179829:49"/>to your minde the inexpreſſible enormity of your Apoſtaſie &amp; rebellion; for what crime more abominable, <hi>quam adverſas Chriſtum ſtare, quam Eccleſiam ejus diſſipare; quam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra unitatem Eccleſiae &amp; concordem populum Dei haere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ice pugnare; quam fraternitatem &amp; amicitiam Chriſti &amp; ſanctorum ejus per Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſiam deperdere, Religionem veram, anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam &amp; ſanctam blasphemando?</hi> Oh <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew!</hi> reclaim, come along, enter into <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſhip for ſafety; <hi>quam tu in baptiſmate aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiſti navigaturus in ea ad littus foelicitatis eternae:</hi> and from which through Satans il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions <hi>te in mare magnum errorum praeceps <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rojeciſti:</hi> forſoooth, becauſe you could not by your poor reaſon or ſences comprehend the wonders and many miracles in the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament of the Euchariſt, you threw your ſelf headlong moſt precipitouſly into an ocean of errours and deceit, fooliſhly as it were following the vain ſteps of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who deſpairing of being able to finde out the reaſon of the Sea's ebbings and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, threw himſelf headlong into the main Ocean, ſaying, <hi>ensentium quia te non capio, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u me cape.</hi> In all reaſon, I think it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to every one, that the will and word of the Almighty, cannot or ought not to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to ſuch a poor pitiful thing as man is; man muſt be led by it, and not draw it to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leaſure, by adding or diminiſhing, chop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:179829:50"/>and changing as he liſts: wherefore our bleſſed Saviour, when ſome, upon the doctrine of the real preſence they had heard him deliver, doubted and ask'd him, with a <hi>quomodo, how can man forgive ſin?</hi> and again, others ſaid, <hi>how can he give us his fleſh to eat?</hi> It is very obſervable, that our Lord never went about to ſatisfie their curioſity, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to them how or in what manner it might be done, it being indeed below the Majeſty of God, to give his vile vaſſal a reaſon of his will, but he ſingly repeated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain his aſſertion, without ſhewing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability or poſſibility thereof; <hi>verily, verily, I ſay unto you, unleſs you eat of the fleſh of man and drink of his bloud, you ſhall have no life in you:</hi> hereby giving us to underſtand, that the inſtitutions and will of God, are not to be ſubjected to the underſtanding of man, but humbly to be accepted with ſubmiſſion and lowlineſſe, as the will of that infinite ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power, unto which mans underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the whole creation is ſubjected. I contemplate you as becomes another <hi>Jonas</hi> in the midſt of the tempeſtuous ſeas of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie, hereſie and rebellion: <hi>O utinam, uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam ſummus providentiae Pater qui projecto in mari Jona, piſcem grandem praeparavit, digna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur me nunc tibi merſo in impietate tua loco piſcis illiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> praeparare ut ſicut animam tuam in ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tre cordis mei per commiſerationem porto,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:179829:50"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ta illam in aridum coeleſtis ſalutis portum evo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ere valuiſſem:</hi> O <hi>Andrew!</hi> Let me be to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou a whale to comfort and preſerve your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul from utter ruine; be you another <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as, accelera veni, &amp; deglutiam horrendum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eccatum tuum, apoſtaſiam tuam, fragilitatem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uam, ſcandalum magnum datum injuriam per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e illatam Deo vivo, &amp; vivo, ſanctis clero, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uloque Hiberniae: accede confidenter, Andrea, &amp; ſecure &amp; pacate introducam te in conſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tum offenſi Creatoris Redemptoris &amp; glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oris tui ut miſereatur tui?</hi> come along into the ark of ſanctification and mercy, with the wandring pidgeon, that returned, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no reſt abroad, and bring in your break that lovely green olive-branch, <hi>Credo unam ſanctam Eccleſiam Catholicam;</hi> abide not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad with the raven, feeding on ſtinking carrion; now I leave you to the ſting of your conſcience more cruel to you then hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh monſters; let it be to you (not what <hi>Menander</hi> confeſs'd, ſaying, <hi>mortalibus cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis conſcientia Deus eſt</hi>) but a light, a guide, leading you to do good and decline evil; for <hi>Synderiſis</hi> is a practical habit of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, not only pointing to you what is good and laudable, but inclining you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to the proſecution of the ſame: this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendent light inſinuates to you not to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſouls of your brothers, by your falſe, erroneous, and damnable doctrine;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:179829:51"/>it diſſwades you from curſing your mothers it excites you to give no diſhonour, affront, or the lye to Chriſt Jeſus; Now I ſay to you what God ſaid to <hi>Cain, ſi male egeris ſtatim in foribus peccatum aderit;</hi> and know, that, <hi>poena tibi est inordinatus, &amp; perverſus tuus animus:</hi> and to conclude, do but obſerve what I ſay to you; there was a man (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> doth relate, <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>exam.</hi>) murthered and left dead, when many flock'd together to ſee the cadaver, the Murdered mans dog, knowing the Murtherer among the croud, made at him, apprehended him, and laid hold of him, barking and biting, until he was conſtrain'd to acknowledge the Murther and his heavy guilt: oh <hi>Andrew!</hi> the horrour of the haynous guilt of your Apoſtaſy doth and ſhall perpetually, and moſt grievouſly bite you, ſting you, and give you no reſt until you be brought to acknowledge your horrid crime, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly cry, <hi>peccavi, Domine, miſerere:</hi> which that you may do, and not be adjudged to the flames of the damned, ſhalbe the daily prayer of your afflicted friends.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:179829:51"/>
               <head>Of Humane Faith. Document 6.</head>
               <p>THe difference between divine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane faith conſiſts in this, that, divine faith is moſt perfect and hath God for its object, and is grounded upon divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which doth promiſe us with infallible, unerring, and undoubted certainty, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy what we believe, and hope for; but hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane faith hath no ſuch object, ground, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or certainty, but is only a morall, caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and probable belief; as for example, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f you <hi>Andrew,</hi> did verily believe that in heaven all great felicities which tranſcend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our lower deſires are to be found, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n hinder you but you ſhould at leaſt do as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch for obtaining thoſe great felicities as for the leſſer, the periſhable; for if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ink you may gain them being a proteſtant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith bare faith without works of char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lineſs, juſtice, pennance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than ſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u have no faith at all; for you believe not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at ſaying of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Hebr. 12. <hi>follow peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th all men, and holin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs, without which no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an ſhall ever ſee God:</hi> humane ſaith you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay have, but not divine, for if a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eves learning to be the only and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnament and beauty of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:179829:52"/>may enable him to a fair employment in time &amp; an honorable memory to ſucceeding ages, this if he believe really and heartily it hath power to make him endure great pains and labour, even catarrhs, gouts, and other diſeaſes, to read and write till his eyes are weary, to deſpiſe the pleaſure of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or delightfull ſports, and even to un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dervalew whatſoever doth not cooperate t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the end of his humane faith, <hi>viz.</hi> the deſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of learning: now, what thing can he imagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo precious, ſo glorious, ſo honorable, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo deſireable, as to enjoy the beatifical viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of Gods eternal glory, and who but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtark mad brain-ſick man, will not endea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vour with all his power and faculties to fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> out the means, helps, and ways, and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpare any labour, pains, or ſufferings wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoever, for to attain to ſuch a happy State<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> O <hi>Andrew</hi> the prodigious ſtories of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrict ſanctity, ſevere diſciplins, rigid mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> tifications, and great ſufferings of Roma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Catholicks in all ages, as in your conſcien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you know; the ardour of their heavenl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> zea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, their deiform intentions, their ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viſhing devotions, ought to be an abundan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> argument to ſhame your dulneſs, ſtupidity lazineſs, and ſupine negliglence, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vince you that ſuch faith as that of Roma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>holicks is not humane but moſt divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> more ſaintlike, more majeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:179829:52"/>more reaſonable, and more productive of pure ſanctity and grace then the bare hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane faith of proteſtants and all other Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries. O <hi>Andrew!</hi> when I to my grief un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand you now ſerve your pſeudo-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late at <hi>Camas</hi> with ſuch hazardous, ſlaviſh, and difficult ſervice, with ſuch undaunted courage, and reſolution, becauſe you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him able to reward you, according to his promiſe to you before you revolted to him, though of his will you are not ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; and yet you are ſo ſupinely negligent and incurious of your ſervice to the great God (from whom you ſhamefully apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed,) whoſe infinitely great power and will rewards all ſuper-abundantly; for if you believe there is ſuch a thing as heaven, and that every ſingle mans portion of the glory there, is far better and infinitely more advantageous then all the riches, content, and pleaſures of this barren world, it is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally impoſſible, you ſhould thus blindly prefer little, before ſo incomparably great profitt, and never ending happineſs. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell what to ſay, but that you are charm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>lothum comediſti.</hi> I believe you are not ignorant of a ſtory of <hi>Homer</hi> in his <hi>Iliads,</hi> who ſaies, that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons travelling towards their native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in their journey, they met trees bearing moſt fair and lovely apples call'd <hi>Lothos,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:179829:53"/>which, for all the fruit was pleaſant and of an excellent raſte, yet it had a ſtrainge pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, that choſe that did eat of the ſame, became ſo drowſie, ſtupified, lazie and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gettful, that they did not minde to give a ſtep forward in their journey to their ſweet native Country: whence comes <hi>lothum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediſti,</hi> as an adage: Oh <hi>Andrew,</hi> you are created for heaven, educated for heaven, you that have labored for heaven many years in appearance to the world, thether you travail as the place and period of your peregrination; how come you not to minde your journey to give a ſtep forward, to advance your conqueſt? why doſt thou halt at <hi>Camas?</hi> how come you to be ſo ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and ſtupidly lazie, by hereſy and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie feeding on <hi>lothos,</hi> vain pleaſure, fair promiſes, deceitful wiles, and ſweet venom of hereticks? O <hi>Andrew!</hi> reflect, reflect, reclaim, reclaim, rouſe up, ariſe, ſhake off your ſhackles and bonds of iniquity; take to your comfort what I have read in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how when the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were captives led to <hi>Perſia,</hi> their Prieſts did hide and bury the holy fire which always did burn on the Altar in the Temple, under ground, in a valley: Many years after, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mias</hi> employed prieſts for to finde out the ſacred fire, who found nothing but <hi>aquam cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſam,</hi> groſs muddy water an mire,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:179829:53"/>O prodigy! no fire but water and that mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and troubled! yet <hi>Neemias</hi> commanded the prieſts to lay the ſacifice on the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars to be offered to God and to ſprinkle the ſacrifice with the muddy miry water, which done, <hi>accenſus &amp; ignis magnus ita ut omnes mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarentur:</hi> O mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>terious ſucceſs! a holy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitor ſays, what! before fire, out of that fire water was engendred! now water and of that fire engendred! O prodigy! what means this? but that for your comfort An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew: <hi>ex igne divini amoris gratia compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis oritur, rurſus ex compunctione Lachri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maram amor &amp; ardor coeleſtis deſiderii, mens noſtra ad amorem Dei inardeſcit,</hi> ſometimes from compuction of heart and from tears the love and deſire of celeſtial things is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred, and ſometimes from the love of God, the grace of compunction, and teares are alſo ingendred. Come along there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore poor <hi>Andrew!</hi> he that continually wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows with dirty ſwine in the mire muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be in the ſame filthy condition: the plague is not more ſpreadingly infectious then ill manners, liberty, evil company and hereticks: ill example is more prevalent then precept, make therefore in time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> men your example, leſt you be made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> example to others. It is related <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e body of the Emperor <hi>Titt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> on the funeral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:179829:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:179829:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:179829:55"/>(according to the Cuſtome of thoſe times) his heart (after the body was reduced all to aſhes) did many times ſpring out of the flames, and being at laſt opened by ſuch who wondred at the ſtrangeneſs of the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, it was found to be full of poyſon which hindred the operation of the fire up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: and when the poyſon was waſh'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, then the fire wrought upon it, and was immediately conſumed to aſhes: oh <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Sall!</hi> the flames and ardour of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine fire of Gods love cannot work upon your heart before the inward venom of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie be waſh'd and cleanſed away by tears of compunction, calling ſincerely upon ſweet Jeſus, <hi>ſaying,</hi> Lord, give me the gift of faith and true Religion; Lord, Jeſus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame my heart with thy love, oh Jeſus, give me a cleane heart from all ſelf ends, ſelf ſeeking, ſelf intereſt and from all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udicate opinion and inſufferable over-wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing pride and malice. O Jeſus, call me back from being ſuch a fiery perſecutor of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed <hi>Julian</hi> was: oh I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> venous in malice, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> me not gangrene in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>diouſneſs againſt this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bas me ego</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lord Jeſus, open <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſee my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> help me
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:179829:55"/>out of my ignorance, <hi>Apoſtaſy</hi> and folly: Jeſus be a Jeſus to me wretched ſinner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>SUre Proteſtants by countenancing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring and advancing to pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erment ſuch Scandalous outcaſt Rubbiſh, do over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw their pretended Religion; by theſe means and ways they ſeek to eſtabliſh and ſtrengthen the ſame: <hi>Andrew Sall</hi> is admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a Miniſter and preacher among Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, yet he from that Proteſtant Sect received no new character, conſecration or Juriſdiction, for that they had none to give; <hi>nemo dat quod non habet:</hi> therefore <hi>Andrew</hi> preaching and acting as a proteſtant-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, authoriſed only by the holy Orders he in the Roman Catholick Church received, it cannot be denied, but that they do own and acknowledge the Roman Catholick Church to be the only, true Mother of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which by many infallible proofs can boaſt of unfeigned prieſtly function, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, conſecration, Miſſion, Succeſſion, antiquity, ſanctity, true M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>racles, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reaſon; all which is in no Sect to be found, but in the Roman Catholick Church: what honour therefore, profit, or proſelits can accrew to the Proteſtants, by ſo much honoring and contenancing our
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:179829:56"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:179829:56"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:179829:57"/>poor Apoſtates made their chief Apoſtles? none, but rather great diſhonour and ſhame; for how can any man in his witts believe, that ſuch vile Runagates who proves faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and perfidious to the living God, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Conſcience, and conſecrated vows, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an prove at all true, real, and faithful to a new-fangled, groundleſs, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Sect, moulded and fram'd by mortal men. It is worth obſervation to ponder, how there was an Orthodox prieſt very familiar with <hi>Theodoricus</hi> an <hi>Arrian</hi> King, who for to inſinuate himſelf into more favour with the King, became an <hi>Arrian,</hi> which when the King underſtood, immediatly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he ſhould be put to death, ſaying, <hi>Si Deo vivo fidem non ſervavit quomodo mihi qui mortalis ſum eam conſervabit:</hi> and you may reade in <hi>hiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. tripar. lib.</hi> 1. c. 7. how <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius</hi> a Gentile Father to <hi>Conſtantinus Magnus</hi> uſed a ſtrange ſtratagem for to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover who among the Chriſtians in his Court were his faithful friends from thoſe that were not, he fain'd to ſet up the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of falſe Gods, and to baniſh from his Court and ſervice all ſuch that would not abjure Chriſtian Religion, and embrace the eſtabliſh'd by him in his kingdom; upon publication whereof many revolted from Chriſtian Religion, for to enjoy the kings favour, many continued conſtant to their
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:179829:57"/>principles; whereupon the King removed from his Court and favour all who proved unconſtant and faithleſs to their religion, not daring in his prudence to truſt thoſe who were found perfidious to the living God, but thoſe who ſtood ſtedfaſt to their faith and conſcience, he embrac'd and emploied in places of truſt and honour. Hence it doth follow, that it is folly to expect that <hi>Andrew</hi> can be true, real, or faithful to Sectaries, that was not conſtant to Gods true ſervice, neither can he be inſtrumental to draw ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proſelites after him in <hi>Ireland</hi> from the Roman-Catholicks, who are brave, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, clear-ſighted Chriſtians, moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of their ancient Religion, for which, and for not going to the Proteſtant Churches, againſt their conſcience, they would not ſuffer impriſonments &amp; forfeitures of eſtats, if they had not been abſolutely certain, that all the Miſteries, and tenents of their anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent faith are purely revealed by God, and faithfully handed to them by their glorious and miraculous Patron and Apoſtle S. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick;</hi> and ſo they chooſe undauntedly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuffer the loſs of all their means and brave eſtates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then make in the leaſt ſhipwrack of their Religion: and they be not ignorant how that it was not for any truth, perfection, or goodneſs in the proteſtant Sect that mov'd <hi>Sall</hi> to revolt to it, neither
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:179829:58"/>for love of more vertues or more ſanctity he deſerted his true antient Mother, but that it was rather for to enjoy more liberty, indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, more pleaſure, more mony, more content, and plauſibility among proteſtants, occaſioned his diſmal ſeparation: yet no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he will not (if he can) periſh alone, he will furiouſly endeavour to gaine proſelites, and will, out of ambition, pride and malice, envenom others though (I am confident), he will catch none but Novices onely in both divine and humane learning, and ſuch as are unſetled in Religion, and wild hair-braind looſe livers, and idle va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grants: Therefore <hi>Andrew</hi> deſiſt from preaching poor ſouls into juſt ſo much as ſhall beget their torture, let them reſt where they finde full ſatisfaction: Oh <hi>Andrew!</hi> deſiſt from fighting againſt God, who is the free diſpoſer of his gifts, and eſpecially of faith, do not expoſe your ſelf dangerously to the indignation of God? do not ſtrive, to drive others and thy ſelf to eternal perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: without queſtion you commit a moſt grievous ſin when you endeavour by artifice of the devil to draw men to profeſs or act contrary to what their ſouls and conſciences believes to be revealed and true; when you wound the weak conſciences you ſin againſt Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. do not deſperatly preach or ſtrive to whip Roman Catholicks
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:179829:58"/>out of their true faith to a way that is but errour and falſhood. Let me now <hi>Andrew</hi> cloſe this Diſcourſe with this; when <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metheus</hi> ſtole fire from heaven to animate &amp; quicken his artificial bodies, the gods for puniſhment of ſo high a ſacriledge, ſtruck him not dead with a ſudden thunderbolt, but (to be more deeply avenged) let him live to be tormented with vultures, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually gnawing on his liver: O <hi>Andrew!</hi> your horrid apoſtaſie and ſacriledge exceeds all crimes imaginable, ſo your puniſhment will be exceeding grievous; for in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky time you ſteal away the heavenly fire of your ſacred function, miſſion and chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter from Gods ſervice, and employ it (though to little effect) to animate and quicken that artificial, earthly, imperfect, dead body of proteſtaniſm: your fire is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to black coals fetch'd from the infernal pit; to preach what in your conſcience you believe untrue, I am ſure is damnable, and to compel others to the ſame is nothing elſe but to drive them to renounce their ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footing in Religion, and the eſſential part in them their reaſon; but let me tell you all your labour, poor contrivements, wretched ambition and oyl will be waſted to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; you do feel I am confident your ſelf tormented with vultures continually gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on your liver: <hi>nam ſequitur ſuperbos ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:179829:59"/>a tergo Deus. Seneca.</hi> and withall, <hi>non exiſtimes impune tibi futurum quod contra De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um pugnare tentaveris,</hi> 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 7. My laſt advice to you is, from the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 9. <hi>quodcunque poteſt manus tua operare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanter, quia nec opus, ne ratio, nec ſapientia apud inferos quo tu pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>peras.</hi> ah dear <hi>Andrew,</hi> be wiſe, return to thy ſelf, confider theſe things, work according to them, that you may be happy, according to the true pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your true friend and well-wiſher, in the beſt things, <hi>J. E.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:179829:59"/>
            <p>A COUNTER-POYSON For to Enchant that Enchanted, Enchanting Forſworn Wretch ANDREW SALL APOSTATE. Miſerably wandring in the Region of Nothing. <hi>Thou haſt not lied to men but to God.</hi> Acts 5.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
